Hello and welcome
to Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 4: Assembling
a Multiparadigm Toolset.
In this section,
we are looking at various
algorithms and techniques
that allow us to analyze the data
from the perspective
of multiparadigm data science,
maintaining a workflow
driven by questions.
We've looked at classification
as a technique
to answer questions of the type:
Is this A or B?
Does the sample belong
to class 1 or class 2?
For example: Is the image of
a healthy or a cancerous tissue?
Is an individual
high credit risk or low?
And so on.
Now let's look at
predictive modeling techniques
that allow us to answer questions
like how much or how many.
For example:
How much should
the price of a home be?
How many runs will a baseball
player score in the season?
What will be the yield
of a power plant this month?
And so on.
Regression is the task that
seeks to answer such questions.
While classification
attempts to predict
a discrete class label
for the sample,
regression aims to compute
a continuous target value
or number,
given the features
of the sample.
Just like classification, it is
a supervised machine learning task
that uses training examples
to learn.
Here's some training data
where each sample
has two features,
age and income,
and a prerecorded credit score.
This is the target value we'd
like to predict for new samples.
Using this data,
we'd like to infer a function
to map from the feature values
to the numeric target,
and once we have that function,
we can use it to predict a target
when given the feature values
of a new data point.
In linear regression,
the model or function
which predicts the target
or response variable—
that is, the score in this case—
uses a linear combination
of the predictor variables
or features—
in this case, age and income.
Here is the predicted credit score
for a new sample
with age 35 and income 65,000,
and this is the fitted model
against the data points,
showing the credit score
for an income of 50,000
across an age range of 20 to 60.
While linear regression is
a commonly used technique,
it is far from being the only one.
The Wolfram Language has
a machine learning superfunction
Predict,
which facilitates
the multiparadigm project workflow
by automating the process
of learning a PredictorFunction,
selecting the optimal algorithm
according to the available data.
Using this dataset with height,
gender and age,
we can use Predict
to create a function
that will predict the age
from height and gender.
Predict is able to handle
different types of data,
including numerical, textual,
sounds and images.
Here's another example
where the input is
the image of a gauge reading
and the output is
the actual numeric value
of the reading.
The predictor function
can predict a value
given a single new input
or a list of inputs.
And while it provides
the predicted value by default,
it can also be asked
for a distribution
of the predicted value
conditioned on the input.
We can get
more detailed information
about the predictor function
to understand
what is actually going on
behind the automated
machine learning.
Let's look at another example
of training a predictor
to predict the mean value
of properties
in a neighborhood of Boston,
given certain features
of the neighborhood.
It's not enough to just create
the predictor function.
We need to evaluate
the performance of this function
to see if it is
really making sense—
if it will predict reasonable
values for real-world samples—
so we test and measure
its performance
against some test data
with actual known target values.
A comparison plot shows
the predicted values
against the actual values,
the dashed straight line
representing
the perfect predictions.
And the standard deviation
gives the root mean square
of the residuals.
Here is a complete report
on the predictor's performance.
While Predict provides
the convenience
of automated machine learning,
it also allows the freedom
to customize the training process
by selecting the method as well as
setting its hyperparameters.
This dataset has
the average daily wind speed
at 12 meteorological stations
in the Republic of Ireland
from 1961 to '78.
Let's use the data from January
of each year from '61 to '77
for training
and reserve the data
from January of 1978 for testing.
We will try to learn a predictor
to compute the value
of the wind speed at Dublin
as a function of the wind speeds
at other places
and also the date.
The gradient-boosted trees method
produces a prediction model
in the form of an ensemble
of decision trees.
The trees are trained sequentially
with the goal of compensating
for the weaknesses
of previous trees.
We are using it for regression
in this example.
Here's a comparison
of the predicted values
for the test data
with the actual values
of wind speed.
The residual plot
and the residual histogram
show the predictions are mostly
trailing the actual values.
These are the hyperparameters
selected by the automated
machine learning procedure.
We can choose
to retrain the classifier
and tune the hyperparameters.
For example, let's set the value
of the BoostingMethod
to GradientOneSideSampling
and retrain the classifier.
We can see
how the predictions change
for the new classifier
on the test set.
As mentioned earlier,
Predict attempts to optimize
the choice of an algorithm
based on the input.
It can choose from among
LinearRegression,
NearestNeighbors,
DecisionTrees,
GradientBoostedTrees,
NeuralNetwork, RandomForest
and GaussianProcess.
For this dataset,
let's train a random forest
and a Gaussian process predictor.
Random forest is an ensemble
learning method, again,
that can be used for both
classification and regression.
It operates by constructing
a multitude of decision trees.
The forest prediction is obtained
by taking the most common class,
or mean value, tree predictions.
Each decision tree is trained
on a random subset
of the training set,
and also uses a random subset
of the features
with a bootstrap
aggregating algorithm.
The Gaussian process method
assumes the data was generated
from a Gaussian process.
In the training phase,
the method tries to estimate
the parameters
of the covariance function.
The Gaussian process is then
conditioned on the training data
and used to infer the value
of a new example
using Bayesian inference.
As we can see here,
the Gaussian process predictor
is smoother
and handles small datasets
better than the random forest,
and we can also see
the difference in training times.
Among other ways to customize
the Predict function
to have more control
over the training process,
we can specify
the UtilityFunction.
The default utility function
for Predict
is the Dirac delta
utility function,
which corresponds with the value
for the highest
probability density
being predicted as the target.
We can define
a different utility function
that penalizes
the predicted values
smaller than the actual value,
and now we have
a different predicted value
for the same input.
The performance
of the predictor function
can be optimized
for training speed,
actual runtime speed,
memory usage
or accuracy of the predictions.
This can be done by setting
the PerformanceGoal option.
By default,
it tries to balance
between the prediction speed
and performance.
For a really simple
interpretable model,
the Wolfram Language
offers FindFormula
to find a function or formula
that approximates the data.
Say you want a formula
to calculate prime numbers.
Here are
the first 100 prime numbers.
We can find a formula
to fit the data
and use it to compute estimates
approximating
the next five prime numbers.
Here is a comparison of the fit
with the data
for the first 300 primes.
In summary,
we looked at some
predictive modeling techniques
for regression tasks
to predict target values
for unseen samples
based on values
of previously seen samples.
We looked at the machine learning
superfunction Predict
and some of the algorithms
it can use internally.
We also looked at evaluating
the performance
of the predictor function
and retraining the function after
setting model hyperparameters.
Early on in the segment, we took
a brief look at linear model fit
as a quick way to build
a linear model for regression.
And we concluded with FindFormula,
which builds
a simple interpretable model
for univariate
or time series data.