Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 5:
Get the Message Across.
We have covered
the first four stages
of the multiparadigm
project workflow—
question, wrangle,
explore, analyze—
and now we are in the last stage,
ready to communicate
the results of our analysis.
Hopefully we've found answers
to the questions we set up
in the very first stage,
whether expected or unexpected.
These answers now
need to be communicated clearly.
We have to tell a story
with these answers
in a manner that the audience
appreciates and finds useful.
Visualizations form
an integral part
of this stage of the workflow.
Pictures can communicate
a lot more than tables of numbers.
Let's look at a few examples
of creating
interesting visualizations
in the Wolfram Language.
These are the populations
of the G8 countries.
Hard to decipher anything
from a bunch of numbers like this,
but seeing them in a bar chart
helps us compare the numbers
much better.
Let's go through a few steps
to annotate this picture
so that it can convey
all the required information
in one glance,
starting out with labels
for the bars.
Now we know which bar
represents which country,
but the labels are too crowded
here at the bottom.
Let's place them above the bars.
Actually, it might look neater
to place them in callouts.
Okay, but what do these bars
really represent?
We know we've charted
the population of these countries,
but to make sure
our audience knows it too,
we need to label the axes.
We could provide
a frame for the chart
and use the frame label
as an alternate way
to label the axes.
Let's remove the top
and the right frames—
they look a little crowded—
and let's also set a PlotLabel
to provide a caption
for this chart.
This chart conveys
the information well enough,
but if we want to stylize it
a little more,
a PlotTheme is a quick way
to use prebuilt collections
of style features
to customize the chart.
ChartStyle can be used
to change the colors
and specify other styles
for the chart elements.
Lastly we can set the ImageSize
to view our picture
with just the right dimensions.
That was a simple example.
Now let's try another one:
adding another feature
to the dataset,
GDP per capita
in addition to population.
The RectangleChart
can help us visualize
both pieces of information
simultaneously for each country,
the width of the bar
showing the population
and the height showing
the GDP per capita.
And we know a chart
has no use without labels,
so we label
all the relevant pieces
to ensure that the chart
is interpreted as intended.
Suppose we have
a third feature in our dataset
that needs to be represented
in the chart, life expectancy,
in addition to GDP per capita
and population.
This is a good place
to use a BubbleChart
with the GDP per capita
and the life expectancy
on the x and the y axes,
respectively,
and the size of the bubbles
representing the population.
The bubbles are colored
according to their sizes,
but it is easier to understand
the scale of numbers represented
by using the colors in a legend.
The tooltip, by default,
provides the information
corresponding to the size
of the bubble—
in this case, the population.
But it is easy customize
the tooltips
to provide more information.
For example, we can create
a little table
out of the information available
for each data point
and add this table to the tooltip.
So now we have packed
a lot more information
into this simple chart
without making it crowded
and without compromising
the aesthetics of the chart.
The Wolfram Language
makes it really easy
to make simple visualizations
more engaging
by adding interactivity.
The Manipulate is
a powerful function
that is actually
pretty easy to use.
We can wrap a Manipulate
around this expression,
and now we have the ability
to choose the information
we would like to see.
For the example
we were working with,
we can use Manipulate to choose
between different continents,
and for each continent,
we can then compare
the life expectancy,
GDP per capita and population
for the countries
in that continent.
One last thing about these charts.
It's important to pay attention
to the axes themselves.
As you may have guessed by now,
these bubble charts were inspired
by the famous bubble charts
of Hans Rosling.
At gapminder.org, we can see
the World Health Chart
comparing health
and wealth of different nations.
However, comparing that chart
to our chart,
we see the spread of the countries
is not quite the same.
Of course
we could take away the outliers
to focus on the range
within which
most of the countries fall
with their national income
per person,
but it is only when we examine
the x axis in the original chart
we see that it is plotted
in the log scale.
We make the adjustment,
and now we see more clearly
the main message of this chart—
that really, most countries
are in the middle
of the health-wealth scale.
Here are a few other examples
of visualizations.
Electricity production by country
for the G6 counties.
For each country,
the breakup is shown
across the different sources
of production.
This example shows
the top petroleum-producing
countries of the world
using a geographic visualization
function, GeoBubbleChart.
Graphs are a great tool
for visualizing relationships
between data samples.
This graph shows the words
nearest to "wolf",
connecting each word
with the two words nearest to it.
This graph shows
how letters in a word occur
one after the other,
or in the case of a sentence,
how words are linked
to subsequent words
in order in the sentence.
The Wolfram Language offers
a large variety
of visualization functions.
For data visualization itself,
there are many specialized
functions that can be used
for visualizing
specific types of data.
Across these functions, a number
of different styling options
can be used to customize
the look and feel
of the charts, plots and graphs.
PlotTheme,
as we mentioned earlier,
is a way to leverage
some prebuilt themes
to quickly set the style
across multiple options.
PlotStyle and ChartStyles
are other useful options
for customizing
the individual elements
in the charts.
There are many different ways
to combine pictures
and arrange them
in a custom layout,
annotate them effectively
and add interactivity
to create engaging infographics.
To learn more about creating
beautiful visualizations
in the Wolfram Language,
please refer to the detailed
hands-on tutorials
linked from
the documentation pages.
Wolfram U also offers
a full-length, instructor-led course
on data visualization
in the Wolfram Language,
as well as many other resources
for learning about visualization
and graphics.