Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 1: The Project Workflow.
We are working on an example
data science project,
looking at the Twitter feed
of Wolfram Research
and trying to capture
some insights from the tweets.
We are trying
to execute this project
by building a workflow in stages.
We have worked through
the first three stages,
where we set up questions,
wrangled the data and explored it.
And now we are at the fourth stage
of the workflow, analyze.
The analysis stage is really where
the multiparadigm approach
becomes so very helpful.
We don't have to
restrict ourselves
to a particular technique
associated with a specific
kind of data or field of study.
The Wolfram Language provides
a large computational toolset
for multiparadigm data science,
and we can pick
a few different tools
to see which one provides
the best answers to our questions.
At the beginning of the project,
we framed questions of the type:
How many?
What?
Who?
And so on.
For each of these questions,
we can pick an algorithm
or technique that helps to provide
a meaningful answer.
Let's start out with how many.
Comparison charts can help
answer questions
about the number of tweets.
Here is a date histogram
from the exploration stage
of the workflow
showing the number of tweets
by year.
The code you see here is available
in the lecture notebook.
We will not go into
the details of the code
in this particular section,
because the aim is to get
a high-level overview
of a project workflow
that embraces
the multiparadigm concept.
Most of the functionality
shown here
will be covered in more details
in later sections.
This chart shows all the tweets
ever made by Wolfram Research.
But in this same way,
we can compare the numbers
of tweets on a particular topic
with a specific hashtag—
for example, #DataScience.
Comparing the two histograms,
we see that while the total number
of tweets went down
from 2017 to 2018, the number
of tweets on data science went up,
and that might be a good thing
to report
to a team planning a Twitter
campaign on data science.
In fact, we can compare
the number of tweets
by month for the past two years,
highlighting for each month
the number of tweets tagged
with a focus keyword or hashtag.
A few things we observe here
are the number of tweets—
they were comparable
at the beginning of the year,
but the 2018 numbers went down
over the summer months.
Also there was a peak
during October of both years,
and that makes sense
when you remember
that's when the Wolfram Technology
Conference takes place.
The focus hashtag
in this example, #DataScience,
has been featured steadily
every month in more tweets in 2018
compared to the previous year.
Here is the total number of tweets
made by Wolfram Research
and the number of days
over which they span,
so we can get the average number
of tweets per day.
During the exploration phase,
we saw date histograms
that showed the number of tweets
by day of the week
or hour of the day.
But if we wanted a quick snapshot
of the hourly numbers
by day of the week,
we would need a comparison chart
showing seven groups
of 24 numbers—
something like this
for the 24 hours in one day,
or this for all the seven
days of the week,
with the days in rows
and the hours in columns.
This is what the number of tweets
from last week looks like.
Again, the code
to create this chart
is there
in the lecture notebook,
and we will also discuss
the associated functionality
in more detail
later in on the course.
Here are the number of retweets
garnered by tweets published
during a specific hour of the day,
to check if
it makes sense to favor
a particular time over others
when sending out tweets.
We see different levels
of engagement
for tweets made
at different hours,
but we can't be sure if this was
the time or the content
of the tweet,
or even some specific user
mentioned in the tweet
that sparked the engagement.
We could try to predict
the popularity of the tweet
in terms of the number
of retweets it gets
based on its features.
Predictive analytics, another tool
from the multiparadigm stack,
can be helpful here.
Supervised machine
learning algorithms
like LinearRegression
or DecisionTrees
could be used to predict
the number of retweets,
given the features of a tweet.
As usually required
in machine learning,
let's split the entire collection
of tweets
into a training and a test set.
We can train a model
on the training set
to predict the number
of retweets for the test set.
For features, we can use
the text of the tweet
after cleaning it up,
and also the time stamp
of the tweet.
A FeatureExtractor can convert
the time stamps
into a numeric vector
and the tweet texts
into a TFIDF vector,
since Term Frequency–Inverse
Document Frequency
is a useful feature
for text classification.
Let's evaluate
the model performance,
and here we come to face
with the unfortunate fact
that it's often hard to come up
with a good predictor model
on the first pass.
We can continue to tweak
the model parameters,
but what's nice
about the automated
machine learning functions
like Predict
is they give you a good place
to start this tweaking.
One possible use
of this simple model
could be to revisit
certain tweets—
for example, this collection
of tweets here at the bottom.
These tweets actually had
a very few number of retweets,
but based on the content
of the tweet and time stamp,
the model thinks these
should have been retweeted
many more times.
So perhaps we could check them
to see if tweaking the timing
or hashtags of these tweets
could have improved engagement.
After working with the numbers,
it's time to move on
to the what part of the analysis.
Basic string pattern matching
and counting are simple techniques
that can help
answer questions like:
What are the tweets
talking about?
What are the hashtags
being used?
In the exploration stage,
we created a word cloud
of the hashtags
to see what topics
were being discussed,
and the same word cloud
highlighted which hashtags
were used most often.
Here is a ranking
of the hashtags
by the number of times
they were used.
If we are focusing
on a specific hashtag,
we can see how often it is used
in comparison
to the others in this list.
Here is #DataScience.
Are there other hashtags
that were used
for tweets on this same topic,
that is, #DataScience?
Here are a few examples.
We notice that typos,
difference in cases,
contractions, et cetera
create multiple versions
of essentially the same hashtag.
For tweets to be visible
in search results,
it would help if the hashtags
were consistent,
and that seems like
an important finding
to communicate
to the social media team.
Let's try another approach
to analyzing this data.
Cluster analysis can be a very
useful tool in data science,
whether for exploration
or actual analysis itself.
Let's try to cluster the tweets
from December 2018.
We can lay them out
in the feature space
of the hashtags,
but we don't really find
distinct clusters here.
The tweets with similar hashtags
appear close together,
but that's pretty much it.
Let's try FeatureSpacePlot
one more time,
but this time
for each individual word
from the tweets,
we use a word vector created
with the global vector model.
No clear clusters emerge yet,
but then again,
these are words in the tweets.
What we want is a clustering
of the tweets themselves.
And to cluster the tweets,
we will need to map
each tweet to numbers
so that we can calculate
the distance between them.
And to visualize the tweets in 2D,
we would need to go
from those numbers
to just a pair of numbers
that can serve as
the x-y coordinates for the tweet.
Here is the text of the tweet
and here is the feature vector
extracted from the text
of the tweet.
Each word is represented
by a word vector of length 50.
So we get a 4-by-50 feature vector
for the 4 words in the tweet.
This is the feature vector
for all the tweets
from December 2018.
To represent each tweet
with a single word vector,
we can sum up the vectors
of each word so as to provide
a sort of word centroid
for each tweet.
Here are the word centroids
for some of the tweets
and the text they represent.
Dimension reduction can reduce
the 50-dimensional
word-centroid vector
to two dimensions.
So now we have a pair of numbers
representing each tweet,
and we can create a scatter plot
to view them.
We can try to find
clusters in this data,
leaving it to the FindClusters
function to automatically select
the appropriate
clustering algorithm.
We can specify the number
of clusters we want,
as well as
the clustering algorithm.
Here are the two clusters found
when all 50 features
of the word centroids were used,
with the help of the KMeans
clustering algorithm.
And this is what each cluster
of the tweets
seem to be talking about.
Can we leverage the inherent
grouping of the tweets
to automatically assign a certain
label to each group of tweets
based on their textual features?
So for that, classification,
another supervised
machine learning technique,
would be a useful tool.
A pre-trained sentiment classifier
can quickly label the sentiment
for each of last month's tweets—
mostly positive and neutral.
It might be more interesting
to see if we can classify
whether a tweet gets
a specific hashtag
based on the content of the tweet.
So for #DataScience, here
are the tweets that were tagged
with this particular hashtag
prior to December 2018.
They can be
our positive samples.
Let's also pick out
a number of tweets
that did not have any mention
of data whatsoever in the text.
These will be
our negative samples.
We can now train a classifier,
which should then be able
to predict a label,
DataScience or NotDataScience,
when given a the text of a tweet.
We could potentially use
this classifier to suggest
whether a tweet could be tagged
as #DataScience or not.
Let's try to use it
on last month's tweets.
Here are the predicted
labels, hashtags
and the text of the tweets.
This one seems reasonable.
Not sure about this one.
Well, at least those
predicted DataScience
are worth revisiting
to make sure the hashtags
are being chosen appropriately.
Let's try one more resource
from our collection
of multiparadigm
data science tools
for the analysis stage: graphs.
During exploration,
we visualized the network of users
who were most often mentioned
in the Wolfram Research tweets,
as well as in tweets
by other users
mentioned by Wolfram.
Within these graphs
we can look for communities,
that is, groups of users who have
more connections within them
than with others
outside the group.
and we can explore
these communities
for shared interests.
We did gloss over
the code in this segment,
because the intention
was to exploit
the multiparadigm approach
in the analysis stage
of building a project workflow.
We will move on to the next
and final stage of the workflow,
communicate.
This is where we will discuss
different ways
to put together our findings
so that it best communicates
the information according
to the needs of the audience.