Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 5:
Getting the Message Across.
Once we have put together a report
or a computational essay
outlining the results
of our analysis,
it's time to share it
with the audience,
and the easiest way
to communicate the results
is to publish it on the web.
Wolfram Notebooks can be
easily shared.
This is how we could do it
from the desktop product
using the menu.
Once published, we can either
copy and share the link,
or visit the link to check
if the published version
appears as expected.
We can also share
the cloud notebooks themselves
from the menu here.
Our audience can either simply
read the results, or better still,
interact with the notebook,
make their own copy
and edit it in the cloud itself,
or download for further work.
In the spirit of automating
the multiparadigm workflow,
we can incorporate the step
of publishing the results
at the end of the workflow
using the function CloudPublish.
By default it makes a public copy
of the notebook for all to see
with AutoCopy set to True
to allow the readers to copy
and edit their own copies.
This access can be restricted
by setting the permissions
as well as other options
for CloudPublish.
Another way to put content
on the web is to deploy it
to the Wolfram Cloud
using CloudDeploy.
With CloudDeploy, you can deploy
a single expression.
It may be
a simple static expression,
or it can be a complicated
interactive content
like a Manipulate.
This Manipulate shows
the population by country
for each continent
chosen from the dropdown.
It can be directly deployed
to the cloud
with the interactivity
of the content
preserved just fine.
Beyond an expression
or an interactive piece,
we can deploy entire notebooks
to the cloud.
Finally, if we have
our custom website
and would like to add
some of the computational results
from our analysis to this website,
we could deploy cloud objects
and incorporate them
in the website or web product
using EmbedCode.
This is a timeline plot
of the notable artworks of Monet.
Here is an example
of a very simple webpage,
which is right now
pretty uninteresting.
But we can use EmbedCode
and add our timeline plot
to the page
as a deployed cloud object.
By default, a CloudObject
is private
and cannot be accessed
by other users.
To share it with others,
we have to set the permissions
to public or to specific users.
Let's just adjust the width here
and reload our page
to see the new content.
So far we've looked
at passive content,
which does not require
any input from the user.
However, if we would like to share
the end results of our workflow
in an interactive fashion,
we could create a simple microsite
that does accept
input from the user.
The form is the building block
for creating a microsite.
It has three main parts.
It has the FormObject,
which makes the HTML form.
It has the input fields
and other specifications.
Then there is a pure function
that specifies what to do
with the input.
Finally, there's a return type,
which is optional,
but it specifies how the result,
after the pure function
is evaluated,
is returned back to the user.
Here is a simple form.
This is the FormObject here,
showing that it accepts
only one string input.
This is the pure function,
which apparently it shows
the image of Yoda
and adds the text,
"May the force be with you,"
to the input string provided.
It returns the result
as a PNG image.
This is a slightly more
complex form
that accomplishes a lot
in a few lines of code.
It leverages the powerful
built-in image
processing functions
to create an Instagram-like
image filtering app.
It accepts as input an image
and the choice of filter.
Then it applies the filter
chosen to the image
and returns the result.
There's more about
the functionality
for generating forms
and webpages
in this guide page here
on creating forms and apps.
The tutorial
Advanced Web Form Creation
provides additional resources
for the creation
of more advanced web forms.
In summary,
we looked at CloudPublish
as the easiest way
to share our work.
CloudDeploy allows
more custom options
to deploy objects and expressions
to the cloud and use them as well.
Finally we looked
at FormFunction and FormPage,
both functions to create
simple interactive microsites.
This brings us to end
of the stage communicate
in our multiparadigm
project workflow.
We hope you will be able to use
one of the many options
we discussed
to communicate the results
of your analysis
and share it
with the rest of the world.