Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 1: The Project Workflow.
We are now ready
to work on the last stage
of our multiparadigm
project workflow.
We have gone through
the first four stages:
setting up questions, wrangling
data, exploring and analyzing it,
and now we would like
to communicate
the results of our analysis.
The data that we
have been working with
are the tweets made
by Wolfram Research.
We have extracted some
useful insights from this data,
and it seems like the results
would be of interest
to the social media team.
Before we present our findings,
it might be useful
to keep two points in mind.
One: what are the needs
of the intended audience—
in this case,
the social media team?
What are they interested in?
What will they find useful?
This will be key in communicating
the results effectively.
The word clouds we created
during the exploration
and analysis stages nicely capture
the focus of the tweets,
and seems like a useful result
to share with our audience.
On the other hand,
the feature space plot
of the words from the tweets,
laid out in the feature space
of word vectors—
it was an interesting picture,
but not particularly informative
in the context
of a monthly Twitter report.
So we might not want
to include that
in the story that we want to tell
this time.
Secondly, as we put together
the presentation,
we would like to set up the code
so that the end data product
of the project—
whether it's an app, a microsite,
a report
or just a piece of visualization—
we would like an automated
or at least semi-automated setup
to recreate it again and again,
whether for reproducibility
or for comparative analysis.
Let's put this together.
It's a little bit like looking at
what you have
in your fridge or pantry
and putting it all together with
a recipe for a delicious meal.
What do we have so far?
To talk about the numbers, we have
a few different comparison charts
showing the number of tweets
by year, by month,
by day of week and hour of day.
We also have the total
number of tweets,
average number of tweets per day—
all useful pieces of information.
To talk about the content
of the tweets,
we have the word clouds.
Linking the content to numbers,
we have rankings of the hashtags
by the number of times
they were used,
or in case
of a specific hashtag,
which might have been the focus
of a Twitter campaign,
the number of times
different variants
of the hashtag were used.
While the clustering of the tweets
did not reveal
any of the interesting insights
we had hoped for,
we were able to use the features
of the tweets
to train a classifier
that could label a tweet
as a candidate
for a specific hashtag or not.
As for the people
referred to in the tweets,
we were able to create a network
of Twitter handles
mentioning each other.
That could help highlight
the influencers in the network.
We were also able to see
the geographical distribution
of these users around the world.
So these are all the ingredients
we have,
and it's up to us to whip up
an interesting recipe
to put them together
for our audience.
Also, once our preparation
is ready,
we have the choice to serve it up
in a few different ways—
basically use any of the different
tools of communication we have
to convey the results.
Starting out with
simple visualizations—
since a picture is worth
a thousand words,
and audiences are often found
to favor pictures
over the written text
in presentations—
we could combine our pictures
together into an infographic,
the layout and annotations
customized
according to the needs
of the audience.
Instead of flat images,
we could make it interactive,
so someone can click through
for a dynamic comparison.
A good amount of information
can be offered
in a visually
concise presentation
by trying out different layouts
and choosing from a large variety
of visualization functions.
Now if we want to include
more descriptive details
about each piece
of visualization,
with text explanations
and also perhaps the code
so that the reader is able
to run it on their own,
then we could simply write
a report in a notebook—
making it into
a computational essay,
with both code and text
organized structurally
into sections
to walk our users step by step
through the analysis.
A high degree of customizability
in terms of style and structure
makes the Wolfram Notebook
the perfect tool
to create such a report.
We could directly publish it
to the cloud,
either making it publicly viewable
or restricting the permissions,
allowing only specific people
to access it.
The cloud-published report
allows us the option to update it
as needed without having to email
multiple copies,
avoiding a lot of confusion
regarding the correct
or the latest version
of the document.
Once we have the
notebook-based workflow in place,
we can of course use it
over and over again.
For example, we can set up
a report template like this one
and use it to generate a report
on the WolframResearch account
or the WolframAlpha
Twitter account—
it's just another
Twitter account
handled by the same
social media team.
We can also automate the process
of generating the report
by deploying a report generator
to the cloud.
This code will generate a report
on the previous week's
Twitter activity
every Monday at 9am
and email a link to the report
to the designated receivers.
We can manually trigger
the report generation
and see what it looks like,
actually.
Here is the email
with the link to the report,
and it allows me to view it
in the browser.
We can also create
a simple microsite.
This code creates a form that
accepts the Twitter account handle
that your audience
might be interested in
and provides the analysis
for the tweets from that account.
This makes for
the simplest of data products
resulting from
our project workflow.
Any one of these different ways
would help us communicate
the results of our analysis,
bringing us to the end
of our project workflow.
This notebook encapsulates
all the various stages
of our project workflow.
Of course,
being a notebook-based workflow
incorporating
the multiparadigm approach,
we can constantly tweak
and improve the workflow
to incorporate new data
or try different algorithms
or visualization techniques
to create new data products,
all from within the notebook.
Notes and descriptions
trace the different stages
of the workflow in the notebook
and can be easily shared
across teams for feedback.
Section 1 of Multiparadigm Data
Science with the Wolfram Language
provided an overview
of building a project workflow.
In the next few videos,
we will delve into more details
at each stage of the workflow
and take a closer look
at the algorithms, techniques
and computational tools available
for practicing
multiparadigm data science.