Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 5:
Get the Message Across.
Once we have
the cool visualizations
that can tell the story
of our analysis,
we need to put together a report
or a computational essay
that weaves the story together
to communicate our message
to the audience.
While we can create,
edit and work
with Wolfram Notebooks
manually pretty comfortably,
sometimes we need to automate
the process of creating notebooks
in form of reports.
A report can be created
with the CreateDocument function
in the Wolfram Language.
Style elements can be added
to the content of the reports
by specifying the type of cell
we want to include
in the document.
The layout and display
of the contents in the report
can be customized using
Grid, Row, Column,
GraphicsRow, GraphicsColumn
or many other such functions
available in the Wolfram Language.
Here is an example of a report
on the population of the countries
in the South Asian Association
for Regional Cooperation.
It shows
the ten most populous cities
and the increase in population
of the country since 1900.
The script helps repetitively
generate the same report
for each country in the group.
To automate the process
of report generation,
the Wolfram Language provides
the use of report templates.
Let's create one from scratch.
We can add a slot that will accept
the value for the country variable
and an expression
that will get evaluated
when the report is generated.
Here's more code to compute
things that will show up
in the report.
The cell behavior can be changed
to control the appearance
of the final notebook.
We can preview a copy
of the report,
which is generated using
the default values in the slots.
Here's a template
similar to the one we created.
We can generate a document
from the template
by supplying new values
for the slots.
For repetitive analysis
over a list of inputs,
we can use repeating blocks
that allow a template to loop
over a list
of supplied slot values.
This template
with the repeating blocks
will accept a continent
and then loop over the countries
in the continent,
creating a block
or section in the report
for each country
in the final report.
Document generators
can be deployed with driver code
that computes the values needed
to fill in the templates.
We can deploy and run a generator
that produces a daily report
on the performance
over the past seven days
of the three stocks
with the highest trading volumes
on the previous day
for a specific industry sector.
We create the driver here,
and then we can deploy it
to the cloud.
The generation of the report
is done by the driver,
and it is triggered every weekday—
actually, from Tuesday
to Saturday—
for the previous business day
at a certain time.
The generation of the report
takes a long time,
so this is an example of a case
where asynchronous evaluation
is preferable.
A notification email will arrive
at the Wolfram ID of the user
once the report
has been generated.
In summary, we looked
at various options
for creating reports.
We looked at basic commands
to script a report
and generate it repeatedly
for different data.
We also looked at creating
report template notebooks—
simple ones
and ones with repeating blocks—
and using them automatically
to generate reports.
Finally we looked at deploying
drivers to the cloud
that would trigger automatic
report generation and delivery.