Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 2:
Getting Your Data into Shape.
Data preprocessing involves
deriving features from raw data
that are informative
and non-redundant,
and are also suitable as input
to machine learning algorithms
and statistical models
often used in the later stages
of the workflow.
Feature extraction therefore
becomes a very useful step
in the multiparadigm
data science workflow
as it transforms raw data
in a variety of formats
into numeric vectors,
which make it easier
to do things like
applying transformations
like standardization, rescaling,
filtering, et cereta;
performing operations like
Principal Component Analysis
and others;
or simply finding
distances between samples
or even triggering activations
in neural networks.
During feature extraction,
we can convert nominal features
that describe some
qualitative aspects of an object,
usually represented as text
or string, to numbers.
We can convert Boolean features—
true/false, yes/no and so on—
to numbers.
And we can also convert
images and text to numbers.
It's not sufficient to just have
these numbers.
If the numeric features have
different ranges of values,
then we need to have
feature scaling.
Standardization—that is, shifting
and rescaling elements of a list
to have zero mean
and unit sample variance—
is one way to scale features.
In addition
to feature extraction,
we can also use
feature selection
to obtain a reduced set
of features.
Sometimes the original input
may contain redundant
and irrelevant features
that affect the performance
of a machine learning algorithm
negatively.
Feature selection can help
with this problem.
It can improve generalization
of the model
by reducing overfitting,
it can reduce training times
and it can even simplify models
to make them more easily
interpretable by humans.
Feature selection is also
sometimes referred to as
variable selection,
attribute selection
or variable subset selection—
the process of selecting
a subset of relevant features
for use in model construction.
Filter methods work
by selecting features
based on some score calculated
by applying a statistical test
to determine which feature
has the most predictive power.
Wrapper methods select
a subset of features
and train a model,
change the subset
and see if the model performance
improves or degrades.
In forward selection,
features are added one at a time.
In backward elimination,
starting with all features,
they are removed one at a time.
Embedded methods have
feature selection built in
as part of the model
training process itself.
Dimensionality reduction
can be treated as a special case
of feature extraction
and selection,
where data is projected
to a different dimension
than original feature space.
When faced with
too many features,
projecting data
to lower dimensions
helps to avoid
the curse of dimensionality—
poor general performance of models
overfitted on training data.
Dimensionality reduction
also allows
intuitive visualization
of data points
in two or three dimensions
for exploratory analysis.
The DimensionReduce function
automatically selects
the best dimensionality reduction
algorithm based on the data,
but we can also specify
the method we want to use.
For example, in this case
we are using TSNE or PCA.
The FeatureSpacePlot function
automatically extracts features
from the given data
and reduces to two dimensions
and creates a scatter plot.
When faced with a large
collection of data samples,
instance selection can help with
quickly creating a model
for proof of concept.
This involves selecting a subset
of training data
to actually build the classifier.
Instances can be sampled
from a large dataset
either by random sampling
or stratified sampling.
In summary,
we looked at functionality
useful for extracting features
from raw data
and for reducing dimensionality
of high-dimensional data.
We also talked briefly
about feature selection
and instance selection.
This brings us to the end
of the section
Get Your Data into Shape.