Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 2:
Getting Your Data into Shape.
In this section,
we are discussing functionality
that is useful
for data wrangling.
Stephen Wolfram recommended
a 10-step data curation hierarchy
on his blog post a while back.
It shows a path to get data
from the raw digital form
in which it has been collected
to a form suitable for repeated
systematic computations.
Integrating it into the
multiparadigm project workflow,
we now have helpful guideline
for the data-wrangling stage.
Steps 2 and 3 here highlight
the need to wrangle raw data
and store it systematically,
with the data elements arranged
in a structured way.
The structural elements
that can be used
for organizing data include
lists, associations,
datasets, EntityStores
and time series.
Lists are the among the most
basic data structures.
In fact, most file formats are
imported into lists by default.
Let's take a peek at this list
to see the first few rows
of the data.
Nested lists provide a structure
similar to rows and columns
of tabular data.
The 601 rows
of the tabular data here
have become the list
of 601 inner lists,
and the 3 columns correspond
to the 3 items
in each of these lists.
Here's the first row,
and here is how we can look
at the rest of the data.
Here's a look at columns 1 and 3,
or if you choose,
we can look at columns 2 and 3.
Lists can be easily manipulated
for inspection and computation.
The only overhead that we need
to keep in mind
are the indices of the elements
in the list
so we can retain an understanding
of the original structure.
Column 1 here has the cities
and column 2 has the sales amount.
If we want the total sales
for each city,
we'll need to work with column 2.
Associations reduce the need
for this overhead
to keep track of the indices.
They use key-value pairs
to represent the data.
So we have
this dictionary data structure,
where each value
is labeled with a key,
and this key is also used
to access the value.
This removes the need to remember
the meaning of each entry
and strictly adhere
to the sequence of indices,
as we had to do with a list.
We can work directly on the values
of the association,
or if needed,
we can also work on the keys.
We can extract all the keys
or all the values
from the association.
It is easy to construct
associations from lists.
And we can get back a list
of the key-value pairs
from the association if needed.
Here's the sales data from
the previous example,
but this time,
let's use an association
to store the sales
for each city.
Now we can retrieve the
information for a specific city
and continue to be able
to work with the data
for all the cities
in the association.
A dataset is a general way
of representing a hierarchy
of lists and associations
constructed from tabular data.
It provides a flexible framework
for sophisticated database-style
queries and manipulations on data,
while providing a defined,
regular structure
at arbitrary complexity.
We can extract rows
or columns from the dataset,
query it using a function
or composition of functions,
as well as sort, filter
and aggregate rows in the dataset.
Revisiting the sales data example,
here is a dataset of sales figures
with the cities in rows
and months in columns,
and this is how we could query it
for information.
SemanticImport gets the data
directly into a dataset,
and while doing so,
it also uses machine learning
to automatically convert
different kinds of data
into Wolfram Language entities.
For data ordered in time,
it is helpful
to preserve the essence
of this special ordering property.
A series of time-ordered
data points,
like the monthly sales
of the Boston office
in the sales example,
can be stored as a time series.
We can now use
special functionality
dedicated to handling time series
to explore and analyze this data.
Here's a sample forecast
from the model based on past data
and a comparison of the forecast
to the actual data
from this period.
The data curation hierarchy
referred to earlier
recommends
converting data elements
into canonical symbolic forms
of entities.
This helps with augmenting plain
data with additional information
during the data wrangling process.
The Wolfram Language provides
access to real-world objects
as symbolic entities
with their own set of properties.
We can create a richer dataset
by converting
the plain-text representations
of many data elements
into computable entities,
thereby really embracing
the multiparadigm approach
to working with data.
In addition
to the built-in entities,
we can create custom EntityStores
out of our own data.
Here is an EntityStore
of the type "offices"
containing the same information
as in the earlier
sales data example.
It has six entities
of the type "office"
with their own properties
like city and total sales.
This can be now used
in the same way
as built-in entities.
You can find more information
about setting up EntityStores
in this workflow
and explore functions
to work with information
in the relation database here.
In summary, we covered
various structural elements
that can be used
in a multiparadigm workflow
to organize and work with data.
We looked at lists,
associations, datasets,
time series and EntityStores.
We also looked at using
the Wolfram Data Framework
to enrich raw data semantically,
a useful step towards preparing
a structured, computable dataset
as the end product
of the data wrangling stage
of the multiparadigm workflow.
In the next segment, we will
look at dealing with messy data—
removing errors and finding
replacements for missing values—
all part of the process
of getting your data into shape
for exploration and analysis.