Hello and welcome
to Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 4: Assembling
a Multiparadigm Toolset.
The very first section
of this course,
Building a Project Workflow,
provided an overview
of the multiparadigm
project workflow.
Sections 2 and 3 provided
more details
on functionality useful
for the wrangle
and explore stages
of the workflow.
In section 4, we'll continue
with the multiparadigm approach,
and look at different algorithms
and techniques
useful for the analyze stage
of the workflow.
The goal is to assemble
a multiparadigm toolset
that can be incorporated
into the workflow
and used to drive it
with questions.
Instead of restricting ourselves
to traditional techniques
associated with specific
kinds of data,
let's reach out across disciplines
to use the tool that is most
suited to answer our questions.
But before we begin,
let's quickly review
some of the terminology
commonly used in data science.
These have been borrowed
from both statistics
and machine learning.
For a data sample x,
x1, x2 and so on are known
as the features of the sample
or predictor variables
or independent variables.
y is the dependent variable
or the response variable
or output value or label.
The model itself
can either be a function
with associated assumptions
and optimization criteria
used to approximate the behavior
suggested by the data,
or it can refer to a blackbox
represented by an algorithm
that takes training data as input
and produces predictions of labels
and values as output.
Parameters are the values
in the model that are not assumed
by the predictor
or response variables.
A big part of machine learning
often involves learning
these parameter values.
Training is the process
of identifying the function
or the algorithm
and the corresponding parameters
that best represent
the relationship between the input
and the output.
Let's look at a few questions
that data science projects
often try to answer
with the help of data.
To begin with,
we have of the most frequently
asked questions
that is of the type
is this A or B,
or even A or B or C or D or E?
In data science,
this is known as classification—
trying to figure out if a sample
belongs to class 1 or class 2,
so questions along the lines of:
Given an image, can we label it
as a cat or a dog?
Given text of an email,
can we say if it's spam or not?
For text in different languages,
can we label each piece
as English or French
or Arabic or something else?
Can we classify a Facebook post
according to its topic—
say, technology, food, travel?
Supervised machine learning
is a technique
where the algorithm
attempts to learn
from training examples
of input-output pairs
to predict output labels
or values for new input.
Classification perhaps accounts
for the widest application
of supervised machine learning
to real-world problems.
It is the algorithm of choice
if your problem can be posed
as the question,
"is this A or B or C
or D or E," and so on.
So it is a descriptive
modeling task
which tries to predict
the class label of a sample
based on the previously
labeled instances.
Here's some training data where
each sample has two features,
age and income,
and a predefined class label,
high or low,
representing the credit risk
posed by
the hypothetical individual.
This is the target label we'd
like to predict for new samples.
Using this data,
we'd like to infer a function
to map from the feature values
to a label.
And once we have the function,
we can use it to predict a label
when given the feature values
of a new data point.
Classify is
the machine learning superfunction
available in the Wolfram Language.
It's perfect for the multiparadigm
project workflow
as it automates
the process of classification.
It picks the optimum algorithm
internally
according to the available data,
whether it's numeric
or text or sound or images
or any combinations of these.
The labeled training examples
are used to learn
a ClassifierFunction
that can be used
to classify and label new samples.
It can also be used
to find the probability
that the sample belongs
to a certain class.
Here we see how the probability
of the sample belonging to class A
changes as the value
of the numeric feature changes.
Let's revisit
the famous Fisher's iris dataset
that we worked with in
the Get to Know Your Data section.
This famous dataset
has the recorded
sepal length, sepal width,
petal length and petal width
of the samples
from three different species
of the iris flower.
Given these four features,
the classification task
is to predict the species
of a new sample.
Here's some training data
for us to train the classifier
and some test data to see how well
the classifier is performing.
A quick visual exploration
of the features
shows us
that they are well-suited
for discriminating
between the three classes
of species,
and can be directly used
to build the classifier
without any feature engineering.
We feed the training data
into Classify.
Here are the predicted
class labels
for 10 random samples
from the test data.
We can find more details about
the classifier that was created.
Along with the algorithm
that was used, decision tree,
we can find out the values
of the various parameters
used for this algorithm.
We can see
how the training progressed
and what was
the performance on the test set.
Accuracy shows how many samples
had their class labels
predicted correctly.
It's not enough
to just build a classifier.
We need to evaluate
its performance
to see if it's providing
reasonable output.
This is where
the test data is useful.
Since we know the labels
of these samples,
we can match them
against the predicted labels
to see how well
the classifier is doing.
Accuracy is one useful measure
of performance,
giving the fraction
of correctly classified examples.
The confusion matrix
is another useful measure,
which shows at a glance
how many samples of each class
were labeled correctly
as belonging to that class
or mislabeled
as belonging to another class.
ClassifierMeasurements
can be used to compute
a whole range of metrics
useful for evaluating
the performance of a classifier.
We can find examples
from one class
that were mislabeled
as another class.
Here are the probabilities
from the classifier function,
which shows why
the mistakes were made.
The iris dataset contained
only numeric features.
Here is an example
where we build a classifier
using labeled images of trees
as input
to predict the species
of the tree as output.
We see the logistic regression
algorithm was chosen,
and it achieved an accuracy of 89%.
All the maples in the test data
were classified correctly,
but there were misclassifications
for eucalyptus, oak and pine.
These were
the best-classified samples
with 100% certainty,
and these were
the worst-classified samples.
These are the samples
of eucalyptuses
misclassified as oaks.
Here's yet another example
of building a classifier
using text input.
We import the text
from works of famous authors
like Shakespeare, Jane Austen
and Agatha Christie.
Now let's try to train a classifier
on these texts
to predict the author when given
a sample of his or her writing.
A simple Markov model
is able to do a good job
of predicting the author
from a sample of their writing.
Classify can be configured to use
one of the many well-known
classification algorithms
as a method,
whether it's logistic regression,
nearest neighbors, Naive Bayes,
decision trees,
gradient-boosted trees,
random forests, Markov models,
support vector machines
or even neural networks.
Let's compare the performance
of two different classifiers
trained on the same data.
One is set to use
logistic regression
and the other Naive Bayes.
We see that
the decision probability
for a sample belonging to class A
reduces gradually
for the logistic regression
classifier,
whereas it is a sharp change
for the Naive Bayes classifier.
Classify can also be customized
by setting a specific value
as the indeterminate threshold
so that the classifier
attempts to make
a confident prediction
only when the probability
of the sample belonging to a class
is high enough.
Since we set
the IndeterminateThreshold
to a high value of 0.9
in this example,
the classifier does not
make a decision
and instead just returns the label
as indeterminate.
This can be useful
in fine-tuning the performance
of a classifier
to avoid false positives.
Classify can also be customized
to assign a specific utility value
to each possible pairing
of actual and predicted labels.
For example,
in this mushroom dataset,
the classifier tries to predict
whether the mushroom
is edible or not.
Each record is a mushroom sample
along with its label,
edible or poisonous.
Once we have trained a classifier,
we can compare
the predicted
versus actual class labels
to see how many
poisonous mushrooms
got predicted as edible.
In this scenario, we'd really
like to avoid false positives,
that is, poisonous mushrooms
getting labeled as edible.
We can set the utility function
to penalize such predictions
more than the false negatives,
that is, edible mushrooms
being classified as poisonous.
We'd also like the classifier
to declare labels as indeterminate
for decisions that are not clear,
so we set up a utility function,
as seen here.
The new classifier
trained with the utility function
predicts many more samples
as indeterminate,
but also has
fewer false positives.
Lastly we can tune
the performance of the classifier
by setting a performance goal.
A classifier's performance
can be optimized
for training speed,
actual runtime speed,
memory usage
or accuracy of predictions.
Here is a comparison
of the training times
of two classifiers
with different performance goals.
Naturally the training time
of the classifier
whose performance
is being optimized for accuracy
takes longer to train.
In summary,
we looked at classification
as a supervised
machine learning task
for predicting labels
for new samples,
with the help of a set
of previously labeled
training samples.
We applied the machine learning
superfunction Classify
on various datasets
with numerical features,
images, text or even combinations
of different types.
We used ClassifierMeasurements
to evaluate the performance
of the classifiers,
and we looked at different options
available for customizing Classify
to suit the need
for the task at hand—
among them Method to use a
specific classification algorithm,
UtilityFunction
and IndeterminateThreshold
to control predictions
and PerformanceGoal
to optimize performance
according to different criteria.