Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 3:
Get to Know Your Data.
We are talking
about exploratory data analysis
as a way of getting to know
your data
before really starting to use it
for modeling or machine learning.
We've looked at some tools
for basic visual exploration
of the data—
a scatter plot or a simple
clustering of the samples—
things we can easily try out,
even if we have no idea how we
want to proceed with the analysis.
In addition to
these traditional EDA tools,
there are many different techniques
we can borrow from various fields
to look at
our own data differently.
A word cloud provides
a quick intuitive understanding
of the most commonly occurring
words in a piece of text,
but we can also use it
to visualize data
any time we are trying to find
the most commonly occurring
elements in a list.
For example, to find
the most popular registered
official language
in the countries of the UN,
we could look at the counts
or we could look
at the word cloud,
which allows us to quickly
identify the most popular ones
in comparison
to the other languages.
With two-dimensional data
like the Old Faithful
geyser eruptions
or the Fisher's iris samples
where we can compare
two features at a time,
it's easy to lay out the samples
in two dimensions
and look at them.
But with more complicated data
with multiple features,
it's hard to visualize the data
without significant preprocessing.
The Wolfram Language provides
a multiparadigm tool
to easily visualize samples
in feature space
across different types of data.
FeatureSpacePlot,
given a list of samples,
it lays them out
in an appropriate feature space
for exploratory analysis.
It uses sophisticated pretrained
feature extractors
for specific types of data—
like images, text or audio.
Graphs are a great tool
for information visualization.
Highlighting graph elements
helps information stand out.
By using
algorithmic graph layouts,
much of the structure in a graph,
such as connected components,
becomes self-evident.
These are the countries in Asia
and the neighbors
with whom they share a border.
Laying them out in a graph,
it becomes clear
which are the hubs sharing
borders with many neighbors,
and which seem to be
the more geographically
secluded countries.
Superimposing geographically
distributed data on maps
can provide insight
into the relationship
of the data
with the geography of the place.
These are the earthquakes
of magnitudes 7 or higher
around the world since 1980.
Superimposing their locations
on the world map,
we see they occur
in a specific geographic region.
A GeoHistogram highlights
the most seismically active parts
of this region
and reminds us
about the Ring of Fire.
Timeline plots show
when events occur
relative to each other.
Here is a TimelinePlot
of the earthquakes
of varying magnitudes
around Japan in March of 2011,
and we can see
this cluster of aftershocks
in the days right after
the Great East Japan Earthquake
and tsunami
that destroyed the Fukushima
Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant.
In summary, we looked at
a few nontraditional tools
for visual exploration of data.
With a multiparadigm workflow,
you can leverage functionality
from across disciplines
to quickly establish
relationships between different
types of features in the dataset
or to just look at your data
very differently.
Some of the tools we looked at
in this segment are word clouds,
feature space plots, graphs,
geographics and timelines.