Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 4: Assembling
a Multiparadigm Toolset.
A review of tools available
for assembling
a multiparadigm project workflow
cannot be complete without
the most popular
machine learning technique
of the recent times,
the neural network.
And we have good news
and bad news on this account.
The good news is that
the Wolfram Neural Net Repository
and the neural net framework
in the Wolfram Language
makes it really easy
to incorporate
this powerful technology
into our project workflow.
The bad news is that
we could never do justice
to covering this topic
in just ten minutes.
But we could look at
the resources we have available
to incorporate neural networks
into our multiparadigm
project workflow.
The Wolfram Neural Net Repository
provides access
to tried-and-tested
pre-trained models,
and we can use them as is
or modify them as required
with what is known
as net surgery.
This is definitely
the recommended way
to get started with neural nets.
However, if we need to to build
neural nets from scratch,
we can do that as well
using the symbolic architecture
provided by
the Wolfram Neural Net Framework.
The Wolfram Language Neural Net
Framework is built on MXNet.
Apache MXNet is an open-source,
deep-learning software framework.
It is portable, scalable
and allows for fast model training
on multiple GPUs.
It is supported
by Amazon Web Services,
Microsoft Azure,
NVIDIA GPU Cloud,
and it can be used either
directly or via an interface
like the Wolfram Language,
as well as other languages
like C++, Python, et cetera.
The usefulness of frameworks
is in the common features
they provide
to allow us to build
and customize neural nets easily.
With frameworks,
we can build networks
as chains
or acyclic graphs of layers.
The layers process
arrays of numbers,
kind of like neural activities.
Encoders convert input
to numerical arrays,
and decoders convert
numeric results to desired outputs
like class labels or images.
The frameworks provide
implementations of loss functions,
backpropagation,
stochastic gradient descent
algorithms and so on,
and are highly optimized to run
on specialized hardware like GPUs.
Now, neural nets can be used
to perform tasks
like classification or regression.
They can be used
for image processing,
audio analysis,
language modeling
and lots of other
different things.
The Wolfram Neural Net Repository
is a public resource
worth exploring
for the neural net models
and examples
of their application.
For example, this is
the Wolfram ImageIdentify Net V1,
which is the power
behind the Wolfram Language
function ImageIdentify.
It can identify
the main object in an image,
which is an image
classification task.
The pre-trained neural net model
can be downloaded from the repo
and used on new images.
The Vanilla CNN
for Facial Landmark Regression
determines the locations
of the eyes, nose and mouth
from a facial image.
It outputs numbers
representing the coordinates
of these points on the image,
and can be used
by other functions
to highlight the points
on the image.
Neural nets are being
increasingly used
for various image processing
applications—
for example, to solve the problem
of segmenting an image
of a driving scenario
into semantic component classes,
as done by the Dilated ResNet-105
neural net model.
To use this model,
we need an evaluation function
to handle net reshaping
and resampling
of the input and output.
Integers from the model's output
can be mapped to labels
for each segment in the image,
and thus be used to obtain
a segmentation mask
for the given image.
The colorful image
colorization model,
as the name suggests,
can be used to colorize
a grayscale image.
It recasts image colorization
into a classification problem
by dividing the AB color space
into a number of bins
and picking the final color
for each pixel
according to its probability
distribution over the bins.
The model takes
a grayscale image as input
and outputs the A and B channels
in the LAB color space,
so it needs an evaluation function
to merge the output
with the luminance of the input.
Here is the output
of using this function
to colorize a grayscale image.
The AdaIN-Style
is an image stylization model
that can transfer the style
of one image to another.
Here is an example
of the model at work.
And here is the output
of the Wolfram Language function
ImageRestyle,
which, as we can guess,
uses a neural net internally.
Among other examples
of models in the repository
is Baidu Research's
Deep Speech 2 model,
which converts speech to text—
an end-to-end model
which takes as input
normalized sound spectrograms
and produces as output
a sequence of characters.
For text input,
there is the collection
of GloVe Word Vector models
from the CS department
at Stanford,
which provide vector
representations for words.
Here's an example of using
the GloVe 300-Dimensional Word
Vector model
as a feature extractor
with the FeatureSpacePlot function
to visualize words
in 2D feature space.
Incidentally, this model is also
used for word embeddings
in the Wolfram Language function
FindTextualAnswer,
which itself is a neural net
trained using
the Wolfram Neural Net Framework.
It answers questions
by quoting the most appropriate
excerpts of a text
that is presumed to contain
the relevant information.
The current consensus
in the neural net community
is that building
your own net architecture
is unnecessary
for the majority of applications,
and such attempts
can even hurt performance.
Rather, adapting a pre-trained net
to your own problem
is almost always a better approach
in terms of performance.
Now we have access to carefully
designed and trained models
in the neural net repo.
So instead of going
through the difficult
and laborious task of building
good net architectures
from individual layers,
we can transfer knowledge
from nets trained
on different domains
to our own problems—
a great application
of the multiparadigm approach
to data science.
We start off by looking for a net
close to the problem
we need to solve,
then download the model,
perform minimal amounts
of surgery on the net
to adapt it
to the specific problem
and train it on our data.
Say we have a problem
of classifying old movie posters
according to the genre
of the film.
First, let's find a net
suitable to our problem.
Let's try
the Wolfram ImageIdentify Net V1.
Now the last two layers
are really specialized
for ImageIdentify,
so we can remove these layers
using NetDrop.
It is really easy doing net
surgery in the Wolfram Language
since the nets
are symbolic expressions
that can be manipulated
using a large set of functions,
like NetTake, NetDrop,
NetAppend, NetJoin, et cetera.
So we can use NetJoin to combine
the part of the pre-trained net
with a chain of two new layers
and our specific decoder.
We train this net
on our training dataset,
freezing all the weight
except for those
in the new classifier layer.
Now we can try it on our test set
to see how the classifier
labels the four test posters.
One of the most powerful
applications of trained nets
is to use the knowledge
they have gained on one problem
to improve the performance
of learning algorithms
on a different problem.
This is known
as transfer learning,
and it can significantly
improve performance
when you are training
on small datasets.
Okay, now let's try to build
a neural net
using the building blocks
provided by the framework.
The LeNet was a pioneer
neural net model
that was released in 1998
to solve the task
of image classification
using convolutional neural nets.
It used the MNIST database
of handwritten digits,
which contained 60,000 training
and 10,000 test grayscale images
of handwritten digits.
The LeNet model was trained
to identify the digit
from the image.
Here's the pre-trained model
from the Wolfram Neural
Net Repository.
We can construct a neural net
similar to the LeNet model
by putting together
different layers.
This network takes as input
a 28 by 28 grayscale image
of a handwritten digit,
and outputs an integer
between 0 and 9,
the class label for that image.
Now a neural network's performance
really depends on the parameters
of the network.
During the training process,
we need to fit
all these parameters
with the help
of the training data.
Initially, the network parameters
are unknown
and set to random values.
In this state, the network will
just return some random result.
So we train the network
from scratch.
NetTrain takes care
of many details automatically,
such as selecting
an appropriate loss function,
attaching encoders and decoders,
initializing the weights
and biases,
choosing the optimizer
and the batch size,
and running
the backpropagation algorithm.
Let's test the trained net.
We can evaluate the performance
of the trained network
using NetMeasurements.
We can also export
the trained model
to save it in the
Wolfram-developed WLNet format
and import it back—
either the whole net
or its elements—
for use later.
Let's take a more detailed look
at the building blocks
of a neural network.
A layer is the simplest component
of a network.
Layers only act on
numeric tensors.
They are differentiable—
differentiability being
a key property
that allows the efficient training
of the nets.
Layers can run on GPUs and CPUs,
and they can do shape inference.
Certain layers have
learnable parameters,
and this is
what makes learning possible
while training the net.
The LinearLayer is
the simplest learnable layer.
It computes a linear combination
of the input,
given some weights and bias—
something that a function
like this would do.
Here is a LinearLayer
with three input nodes
and two output nodes,
and we can initialize
the parameters for this layer.
Here we can compare the results
of our own linear function
using the weights and biases
from the initialized LinearLayer.
The Wolfram Neural Net Framework
provides a huge list of layers
to incorporate
into your neural net model.
Containers.
We usually need to combine
multiple layers together
to do something interesting.
This is where containers
become useful.
Chains are
the simplest containers,
and NetChain can be used to
chain together two or more layers.
This function
is really the computation
that the chain here accomplishes.
Since NetChain cannot really take
more than one input,
NetGraph is used to build
more complex networks.
To accomplish something
that this function would compute,
we need to create a NetGraph.
All of the layers
are differentiable,
and so are the containers.
Containers can be nested,
just like normal layers.
The models in the repository
are almost all
in some form of a container.
Neural net layers require as input
numeric tensors.
To train and use nets
on images, audio, text, et cetera,
we need to use a NetEncoder
to translate the data
to numeric tensors.
This encoder produces a
1 x 12 x 12 tensor from an image.
It can be used on an image
directly or on a file.
A large collection of encoders
are available
for different data types.
The output of a neural net
is also a numeric tensor,
but for a task
like classification,
we would want
class labels as output.
The NetDecoder converts numbers
to non-numeric outputs
for the net.
This decoder will interpret
a vector of probabilities
over classes as a class label.
The probabilities themselves
can also be obtained.
In this whirlwind tour
of neural networks,
we learned about
the Wolfram Neural Net Framework
and the features it offers.
We looked at examples
of pre-trained neural net models
in the Wolfram Neural
Net Repository
and how to use net surgery
to customize and adapt the models
for use in different tasks
for transfer learning.
We put together
a simple neural net
according to the LeNet model
to recognize
handwritten digits of images.
We also looked
at the various building blocks
provided by
the neural net framework
to understand
how they can be used
to design, build and customize
neural net models.