Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 3:
Get to Know Your Data.
In this last segment
on exploratory data analysis,
we'll look at some
of the statistical tools
that can be helpful in developing
a preliminary understanding
of the data.
While visualizations
are cool to look at,
numbers play an important part
in our understanding
of the world around us.
Tukey's five-number summary—
minimum, maximum, median
and the first and third quartiles—
provides a concise summary
of the distribution
of observations.
Since these are order statistics
rather than, say, the mean,
the five-number summary
can be used for ordinal features
as well as features representing
interval and ratio measurements.
Let's revisit
the Fisher iris dataset
that we explored visually in
the first segment of the section
Get to Know Your Data,
but this time,
let's look at some
of the descriptive statistics
for the features.
Here are the mean
and standard deviation
for a single variable, that is,
sepal length for the setosa class.
This table visualizes the
information for all three classes
for different types
of descriptive statistics
like mean, variance,
median, et cetera.
These can also be computed
for more than one variable—
in this case, sepal length,
sepal width, petal length
and petal width.
Here are the descriptive
statistics at a glance
for all four variables
across the three classes.
Among other numbers that can be
useful in understanding the data,
we have frequency counts
that can tell us
about the number of samples
of a particular type,
and we also have
Pearson's correlation coefficient,
which measures the strength
of the linear relationship
between two variables.
While scatter plots can show
correlation visually
in two dimensions,
calculating the linear correlation
for multivariate samples
can be helpful,
especially when we'd like
to use these numbers
for further analysis.
For the Fisher iris dataset,
it seems that features 3 and 4
show strong linear correlation
while features 1 and 2 do not.
As Hans Rosling said,
it's true that, "the world cannot
be understood with numbers alone,"
but he did preface his quote,
saying,
"the world cannot be understood
without numbers."
Hopefully the statistical tools
we looked at in this segment
will allow you to gain a better
understanding of your data,
along with
the visual explorations,
in the setting of a
multiparadigm project workflow.
Ideally as we wind up EDA,
we should be able to answer
the following questions
satisfactorily about our project:
Do we have the data as needed
for the planned analysis?
Is there enough of it?
Does the data seem to be accurate?
Are there obvious errors?
Is the data missing something?
Is the data relevant?
Are there outliers?
Are there some characteristics
of the features
that attract attention right away?
Here is a checklist
that can be helpful
whenever we have a new dataset
and are trying to navigate
the explore stage of the
multiparadigm project workflow.
If you have some data, try to:
Visualize it in feature space
in 2 or 3 dimensions.
Either use pairs of raw features,
or project all features
to lower dimensions.
Create scatterplot matrices
to look at pairwise relationships
between the variables.
Plot distributions of all variables.
Start with a single distribution
for a single variable,
and go on to joint distributions
of pairs of variables.
Overlay plots and graphs
to compare distribution shapes
to histograms.
Look for deviations.
Visualize clusters
to identify outliers,
and also to look
for obvious errors
or gaps in the data plots.
Plot time series data
and identify trends.
Reach out across disciplines
for visualization tools
that may lend a different
perspective on the data.
Last but not the least,
generate summary statistics
for each independent variable
or feature,
and also look
at pairwise relationships
or correlation
between the variables.
Successful EDA
while exploring the data collected
can help identify user stories
to make sure
the downstream analysis
has a real purpose.
It can help formulate
the right questions,
provide clues about what algorithm
to use down the line
and allow tweaking of
the multiparadigm project workflow
to include the right set of tools
useful for answering
those questions.