Hello and welcome
to Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 1: The Project Workflow.
Data science projects
attempt to use data
to answer certain questions
so that you can derive some
useful insights from the answers
and act on them.
A flexible, modular, iterative
workflow can serve as a roadmap
in this quest to get
from data-driven questions
to actionable insights.
Here are five stages in which
we can build up such a workflow.
We start out with the questions,
then move on
to the data-wrangling stage
where we import the data
and shape it.
Then we do some
exploratory analysis
to get an intuitive understanding
of the data
before launching
into the analysis stage
to try different
models, algorithms
and techniques
to dissect the data.
Finally, we try to communicate
the results
in a clear and comprehensive way
to our audience.
What the multiparadigm
approach adds
to this otherwise
straightforward path
is the option to work
with different types of data:
flat files or databases,
audio or images, sensor readings,
data scraped off the web.
And at the same time,
it provides the scope
to branch out
at every stage of the workflow,
experimenting with and assembling
a broad, flexible,
computational toolkit
to incorporate
data processing, analysis
and visualization capabilities
into one
start-to-finish workflow.
And you build
this workflow iteratively,
in the spirit
of agile development.
You keep tweaking
and modifying different stages—
all the while keeping
the original question in mind.
Your workflow is driven
by the questions,
and it is not restricted
to traditional techniques
associated with a specific kind
of data or field of study.
Let's try to use
this workflow template
to execute a simple
data science project.
Let's do some
social media analysis.
We'll look at
the Wolfram Research Twitter feed
and see if we can get some
data-driven insights out of it.
So here are the tweets,
containing text, URLs, hashtags,
mentions of other users,
et cetera.
From this data, we want to create
a report on the Twitter activity—
something like this,
which would perhaps help
the social media team
to strategize
for a Twitter campaign.
The first stage of the workflow
is where we frame the questions.
To get some useful conclusions
from the data,
we need to start out
with the right questions.
We have a list of tweets
made by Wolfram Research.
What can we learn from them?
Now that is
a pretty broad question.
It makes sense to break it down
into few specific questions
that can guide our analysis—
questions like:
How many tweets are sent?
How many of these
are being liked or retweeted?
Which hashtags
are used most often,
which should indicate
what topics are being discussed?
Also, who were mentioned
in these tweets,
to highlight the people involved
in these conversations?
In addition
to the topic-specific questions,
it's helpful to keep in mind
the audience of the analysis
right from the start.
For this example project,
the end audience could be
hypothetically
Wolfram's social media team.
Perhaps they would like to see
a monthly report
on the account's Twitter activity—
a snapshot that presents answers
to questions like how many, what,
who, with regard to the tweets.
Now the questions can be fuzzy
as we start out,
and they can change later.
In fact, more interesting
questions may surface
as we sift through the data.
However, it is important
to set up these questions
at the beginning
with the audience in mind.
Otherwise, with the sheer
variety of things
that we can try with the data,
we might end up wasting time
on unnecessary analysis.
Now that we have some questions,
let's get our hands on the data
and see what we can find out.