Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 2:
Getting Your Data into Shape.
Real-world data can be messy.
It is not enough
to simply get hold of data.
A multiparadigm workflow must
be able to deal with incomplete
or inaccurate data
containing items
that may be even irrelevant.
Data cleaning is the process
of replacing, modifying
or removing errors from the data.
A data cleaning checklist to deal
with these various problems
is a good idea for repeated use
at this stage
of the project workflow.
We can start out by checking
for consistent formatting
across each row
and also across each column.
We can also check
if the feature values
are reasonable and informative—
free of obvious errors.
All feature values must be
within a permissible range,
and we can check with experts
for a reasonable range.
Finally we need to check
if there are indications
of missing data,
and once we've identified
missing data,
we must decide
how we are going to deal with it.
With the checklist in hand,
let's look at ways to clean
the data one variable at a time.
We can look at each variable
featured in the dataset
to identify erroneous values.
If you were expecting
only numeric values,
then there should not be strings
in a particular column.
If all values in a column
are the same,
the feature is unlikely to be
discriminatory or useful.
Informative features
usually span a range of values.
If the observed range of values
appears less than expected,
an unexpected cutoff
may have been applied
across the data.
If the range of values is
different from what is expected,
some form of unit conversion
may be required,
like metric to imperial.
The maximum and minimum
of a numeric feature
should not be outside
the permissible range of values.
Cardinality of a feature
should conform to expectations.
For example, there should be
only two possible values
for a Boolean feature—
true or false.
If we find samples with values
other than true and false,
that is an indication
of a problem.
If the data points come from
a known statistical distribution,
then they should conform
to the parameters
of those distributions.
For a normal distribution
of, say, mean 5
and standard deviation of 2,
12 would be a suspicious value.
Any known or common sense
relationship between features
should be verified with numerical
or logical consistency checks.
Misspellings are
a common source of errors.
Sorting nominal features
can bring misspelled values
next to correctly spelled values
and make it easy
to spot the error.
So how do we
deal with missing data?
We can do it in a number of ways.
For starters, we can simply ignore
the samples with missing values.
That’s easy,
but in a real-life scenario,
you may only have
few samples to work with.
So instead of throwing away
some of the data
that was collected
with a lot of hard work,
it might help to find
reasonable substitutes
for the missing values.
One candidate
for replacing missing values
is the most commonly occurring
value for that particular feature,
or the mean of all
the available feature values
in that particular column.
In certain cases,
it might make more sense
to replace the missing value
with the mean of samples
belonging to the same class
as the corrupt sample
instead of the mean
of all the samples.
It doesn't always
have to be the mean;
it can be the median
or the commonest value
in the class.
We can even pick a random value
to replace the missing value.
Here's an example
where we compute
the mean and standard deviation
to model a normal distribution
and then pick
a random value from it.
We could even attempt to learn
a distribution from the good data
and use it to generate
a random replacement value.
In hot deck imputation,
we pick a good sample—
one with no missing features—
that is most similar
to the bad sample—
the one with a missing value—
then copy
the good sample's feature value
to replace the missing value
in the bad sample.
If the situation demands,
it is not unheard of
data scientists employing
a full-blown classification
or regression model
to predict the missing values.
If we do not really want to make
any changes to the data,
changes like removing
or replacing sample values,
we could just leave Missing
as a special feature value,
and the Wolfram Language would
be able to handle that easily.
Before concluding this segment,
let's look at some useful
Wolfram Language functions
for sifting through the data.
Specific samples can be identified
in a list with the help of Cases.
Samples can be filtered out
according to various conditions
using Select.
Various types of Delete functions
can be used
to remove unwanted samples
from the data.
Pattern matching
along with Replace can be used
to replace missing values
or delete them.
In summary,
we looked at a few thumb rules
for systematically
going through the data,
checking for inconsistencies.
We looked at a few different ways
of dealing with missing data.
We also looked at some
Wolfram Language functions
that can be used
for sifting through messy data.
In the next and final segment,
we will look at feature extraction
and dimensionality reduction
as the possible final steps
of Getting Your Data into Shape.