Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 1: The Project Workflow.
We are working on building
a project workflow
for our example
data science project,
and we have completed the first
and very important stage
of the workflow:
setting up questions
that can be answered
with the help of the data.
In the next stage,
we will actually get
our hands on the data.
Data wrangling involves
importing raw data
and converting it
into a suitable shape
for the rest of the analysis.
To get the tweets
made by Wolfram Research,
we will connect to the Twitter API
and use that connection
to download the tweets.
We have set the username
to be WolframResearch
because this is the Twitter
account we are interested in.
Let's take a peek and see
how the data is structured.
Here are five random samples.
Looking at the fifth row closely,
we see the tweets
each have a unique ID;
the text of the tweet;
something called thumbnailsURL;
date and time
when the tweet was made;
hashtags used in the tweet;
location of the tweet,
which can be empty;
and the user who made it,
which is redundant
because we know
we downloaded tweets
only made by WolframResearch.
Same case with the name
and the ProfileImageThumbnail.
But these two items
should be useful,
the retweet count
and the favorite count,
which can be used as indicators
of engagement
generated by the tweets.
Lastly, there is the URL to find
the tweet on the Twitter site.
This is the underlying structure
of each row:
it's an association
of key-value pairs—
key being the feature name
and value being the feature value
for this particular sample.
One piece of information
not included explicitly
in this structured data right now,
but which might be useful later on
is the list of user mentions
found in the tweet.
But we can parse that
out of the text of the tweets
to get that information.
For example, say this is
a piece of text from a tweet
and we see Wolfram U
is mentioned here.
We can use string pattern matching
to check for the @ symbol
followed by a digit
or letter or underscore—
basically, the rules
that limit a Twitter handle—
and if we find a match,
we pull it out
to be a user mention.
This function here
uses this pattern matching
to get the user mentions
and adds them
back into the data structure.
Let's use it on an example.
Here is the original association,
and here is the same association,
but now with the user mentions
added in.
We can augment our entire dataset
with the additional information
about user mentions
in an easily accessible form.
Looks like the data
is in pretty good shape.
Sometimes an additional
data cleaning stage
may be needed in the workflow
to deal with things
like missing data,
errors in data, et cetera,
or we could just sneak it into
the data wrangling stage itself.
Here is an example of a tweet,
and we can see it has
some characters that are not
really useful for text analysis.
We can easily remove the "& gt",
"& amp" and the URLs
with some more
string pattern matching.
And then we can delete stopwords
like "is," "the," "of," et cetera.
We wrap up these two steps
into a single function
that will clean up
the text from a tweet.
So it seems like we have
our data in shape
and we have some code to
clean up the text if we need to.
We are ready to move on
to the next stage,
which is really
the most interesting part,
because it is exploration.