Hello and welcome
to Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 3:
Get to Know Your Data.
In this section,
we will look at functionality
useful for the explore stage
of the multiparadigm
project workflow.
Exploratory data analysis
is really about trying to gain
an intuitive understanding
of the data.
How are the samples
spread out in feature space?
How do the features
relate to each other?
Without any analysis,
can we just look at the data
and make some sense of it?
We've talked about
setting up questions
right at the beginning
of the multiparadigm
project workflow.
However, the explore stage
is where a lot
of those questions can change
and new questions emerge
as we try to figure out
what the data has to offer.
Sometimes this stage is also used
for data QA—
checking the quality of the data
and assessing whether it is useful
and sufficient for the project.
Tools used for exploratory
data analysis, or EDA,
can be categorized as graphical,
providing pictures,
or non-graphical,
providing stats and numbers;
univariate, exploring one feature
or variable at a time,
or multivariate,
exploring combined behavior
of more than one variable—
usually two.
Humans are visual beings.
Instead of staring
at a column of numbers,
human pattern-recognition
abilities are better used in
visual explorations,
checking for trends,
shapes of distributions,
gaps, outliers and so on.
To literally look at the data
and examine each feature
on its own
or in comparison
with other features,
we can use scatter plots,
bar charts and pie charts,
histograms, box plots,
cluster visualizations,
time series plots and so on.
Let's try some visual explorations
with Fisher's iris dataset.
It has the length and width
of petals and sepals
of three species
of the iris flower.
Scatter plots are a simple
and easy way
to look at the correlation
between two variables.
Here is how the sepal lengths
of the Setosa species
measure against the sepal width.
A scatter plot matrix shows
the pair-wise relationship
between multiple variables.
Here we see how the sepal length
corresponds to each
of the other features—
sepal width, petal length
and petal width.
We can repeat this
for each variable in turn,
thus creating
the scatterplot matrix.
Here is the matrix
showing the relationship
between the four variables
of all the three species of iris.
Now let's look at bar charts
and pie charts,
two other common tools
for visual explorations.
We'll use the Old Faithful
eruptions dataset,
which provides the eruption time
and the waiting time
to the next eruption
for the Old Faithful geyser.
Let's focus on the durations
of the eruptions—
elements in the first column.
We can group the samples
into four specific bins—
less than 2 seconds,
between 2 and 3 seconds,
3 and 4 seconds
and more than 4 seconds.
We can identify in this list
that the fourth number
is larger than the others,
but a bar chart or pie chart
really allows us
to compare these numbers visually
and immediately understand
that the eruptions
more than 4 seconds
are the most common ones.
Some other visualizations
that can be helpful
in exploring the data
are box whisker plots,
which show the max, median, min,
as well as first
and third quartiles.
Violin plots
are similar to box plots,
but also show probability density
of the data
at different values.
Finally, quantile plots compare
the empirical quantiles
of the data values
against the quantiles
of a normal distribution.
Histograms are very useful for
exploring quantitative variables.
They provide an idea
about the shape
of the underlying distribution.
For the duration
of the eruptions,
the histogram immediately shows
two distinct groups.
Paired histograms can help
compare the distribution of values
of both variables.
For example, here are the two sets
of random numbers
from two normal distributions
with different mean
and standard deviations,
and here is the paired histogram
comparing them.
Let's compare the duration
and wait times
from the Old Faithful data
with a paired histogram,
only we have to scale
the duration values
to be in the same range
as the waiting times.
Overlaying plots is useful
for comparing a fit
with the original data,
since humans are better
at recognizing deviations
from straight lines.
Here is a comparison
of the histogram of the wait times
to an estimated distribution
for the Old Faithful data.
The trusty old scatter plot
can highlight obvious correlation
between feature variables,
but it is also possible
to explore correlations
by visualizing
multivariate data in 3D
through density projections
and histograms
based on binning
or kernel density estimation.
Clustering data is often used
to separate data into groups
or to identify subgroups
within a dataset.
It only takes a little bit
of Wolfram Language code
to quickly build an interface
to interactively explore
different clusters in the data,
thereby offering the opportunity
to identify interesting outliers.
Let's look at some other ways
of quickly visualizing
clusters in the data.
ClusteringTree creates
a weighted tree
from a hierarchical clustering
of data elements,
while a Dendrogram creates a tree
where the heights of nodes
are proportional
to intercluster distances.
Before we end this segment,
let's look at
a special type of scatter plot
where one of the variables
is time.
So we have some unit of time
on the x axis,
and plot on the y axis
the change in values
of the dependent variable
with respect to time.
Here is the daily mean humidity
of Champaign, Illinois,
in the last year, showing May
was dryer than other months.
Here's a similar plot
for the weekly mean temperatures
where the winter dips
and summer peaks
are easily identifiable.
These visualizations in time
allow us to quickly spot
any trend in the data.
In summary,
we looked at various tools
for visually exploring our data.
We looked at scatter plots,
bar charts and pie charts,
histograms, box plots,
violin plots,
cluster visualizations
and time series plots.
We hope you will be able to use
one or more
of these visualization tools
in the explore stage
of your workflow
in your next data science project.