Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 4: Assembling
a Multiparadigm Toolset.
We started the course
with the central idea
of developing
a multiparadigm project workflow,
incorporating ideas, algorithms
and techniques
from across disciplines at
different stages of the workflow
to ensure it aims to answer
data-driven questions.
We've already looked
at machine learning superfunctions
like Classify and Predict
to answer classification questions
like is this A or B,
or regression questions
like how many or how much.
Now let's move on
to unsupervised machine learning
to answer questions like:
How is the data organized?
Does the data have
some inherent structure?
Do the samples sort themselves out
into different groups
and subgroups?
Unsupervised learning functions
attempt to automatically discover
patterns in unlabeled data.
Clustering is one
of the most common
unsupervised learning tasks,
which attempts to partition
the data into groups or clusters.
Elements within a cluster
are closer to each other
than to other elements
outside the cluster.
For Fisher's iris data,
if we cluster
based on the numerical features
of petal length and petal width,
the clusters coincide very nicely
with the species of the flower,
the blue dots being setosa
in a two-cluster partition,
and in a three-cluster partition,
the orange dots are versicolor
and the green dots
are virginica—mostly.
In the Wolfram Language,
FindClusters can be used
to partition a dataset
into clusters of similar elements.
It works on all sorts of data:
numerical, text, image,
as well as dates and times.
To cluster any type of data,
what we need is
a measure of how far apart
each sample is
from other samples in the data—
a way to measure
the distance between.
For this
we need a distance function.
A distance function f satisfies
the following requirements.
So identical element pairs
have zero distance,
and all others
have positive distance.
The greater the distance,
the less the similarity
between them.
FindClusters automatically
picks up a distance function
depending on the type of data.
If the e_i are vectors
of numbers,
FindClusters by default
uses squared Euclidean distance.
If e_i are lists of Boolean
true and false elements,
then FindClusters
uses a dissimilarity
based on the normalized fraction
of elements that disagree—
for example,
Jaccard dissimilarity.
If the e_i are strings,
then FindClusters by default
uses a distance function
based on the number
of point changes
needed to get from one string
to another—
for example, edit distance.
We can also explicitly specify
an appropriate distance function
depending on the data.
Here are some useful
distance functions
for numeric data,
Boolean data and string data.
The choice of a distance function
is definitely important
in finding
the right kind of clusters.
Here is an example
with synthetic data,
where changing
the distance function
from Euclidean to cosine
allows the algorithm
to find the clusters
which are obvious
to the human eye.
The other important choice
for identifying clusters
is the clustering algorithm
itself.
By default, FindClusters
tries different methods
and selects the best
for clustering.
KMeans and KMedoids determine
how to cluster the data
for a particular number
of clusters.
DBSCAN, JarvisPatrick,
MeanShift, SpanningTree,
NeighborhoodContraction
and GaussianMixture
determine how to cluster the data
without assuming
a particular number of clusters.
Agglomerate and Spectral
can be used in both cases.
Certain clustering algorithms
perform better than others,
depending on
the natural clusters in the data.
In this synthetic data,
we humans can clearly identify
the cluster
embedded in the center
of what appears to be
uniformly distributed noise.
The KMeans clustering algorithm,
however, attempts to find
two clusters,
and does not work very well
in this case.
But the density-based spatial
clustering algorithm DBSCAN
can easily identify
the cluster in the center.
For more control
on the clustering algorithm,
we can specify Method suboptions
like NeighborhoodRadius
and NeighborsNumber for DBSCAN,
InitialCentroids
for KMeans and KMediods,
and ClusterDissimilarityFunction,
which specifies
the intercluster dissimilarity
for the Agglomerate method.
The specified CriterionFunction
is used to evaluate
the clusters obtained
to decide on
the best number clusters.
In this dataset,
using StandardDeviation
as a criterion function
results in unnecessarily
breaking up the outer ring cluster
into multiple smaller clusters.
However, using the RSquared
criterion function,
only two clusters are established.
There are other
Wolfram Language functions
that use the notion
of distance function
and can be used to group samples
based on their similarity.
Both ClusteringTree
and Dendrogram
hierarchically create clusters
and visualize them as well.
While FindClusters returns
the separate lists of samples
corresponding to each cluster,
ClusteringComponents returns
the indices of the clusters
to which each sample belongs.
The Nearest function
uses the notion
of the distance function
internally
to find elements
closest to a given sample.
While working with samples
in feature space,
FeatureNearest can be used
to create a NearestFunction
that can be used to find
a sample from the training data
that is the closest match
to a new test sample.
We've looked at
FeatureSpacePlot before briefly
during exploratory data analysis.
Given any collection of objects,
FeatureSpacePlot
attempts to lay them out
in an appropriate feature space,
without the need
for fine-tuning details
like converting data
from one format to another,
projecting to lower dimensions
or choosing algorithms
and parameter values.
FeatureSpacePlot can handle
different types of data
like photographs,
texts, et cetera,
and uses sophisticated
pre-trained feature
extractors internally.
Labeled training data is expensive
since an expert
has to manually label each sample.
However, unlabeled training data
is abundant and easy to come by.
If we view clusters
found in unlabeled data
as potential classes,
then we can use clustering
to build a classifier
that will assign labels
to new samples
based on the clusters
it has identified
in the existing data.
Here is a breast cancer dataset
from the UCI
Machine Learning Repository
consisting of benign
and malignant samples
with numerical features extracted
from original images of the cells.
These are
the feature descriptions,
and we see that
the first column is the ID
and the last column is the class.
There are 458 benign
and 241 malignant samples.
Let's ignore the ID
and the class columns.
Let's just
focus on columns 2 to 10.
We can use these features
and attempt to cluster the data,
and then build a classifier
based on that clustering.
Now once we have the classifier,
we can use it on new samples to
predict a potential class label,
malignant or benign,
for a new sample.
Going back to the samples
and applying our classifier,
we find two class assignments
where the first class
has 385 samples,
which look mostly like
the benign samples,
and the second class
has 312 samples,
which has 73 benign,
but 239 of the malignant samples.
So we see that sometimes
cheaper computational methods
can serve as a screen
for classifying samples
that otherwise require
expensive experimental methods
for accurately classifying them.
Of course we can always use
the experimental method
to confirm the classification
suggested by
the computational method.
Given a large amount of data,
it is possible to create
a simple interpretable model
of how the data was generated.
The Wolfram Language function
LearnDistribution
learns a distribution
from the data
that attempts to represent
an underlying process
from which the examples
might have been generated.
Back to Fisher's iris data,
we can train a distribution
directly from this dataset
and use it
to generate random samples.
Here is a comparison
of the generated random samples
in red
against the original samples
in green.
For the simpler case
of univariate data,
the related function
FindDistribution
attempts to learn a continuous
or discrete distribution
from the data itself.
Here is a histogram
of data points
generated from a mixture
of a NormalDistribution
and ExponentialDistribution.
FindDistribution suggests
this mixture distribution
to fit the data,
and we can see
how the fit compares
with the histogram itself.
In summary,
we looked at FindClusters
as the primary function
for cluster analysis
in the Wolfram Language.
We looked at choices
of DistanceFunction
and algorithms that can be used
with FindClusters,
and we also
looked at CriterionFunction
as an option to evaluate clusters
and select the right number
of clusters automatically.
Other functions that can be used
to visualize clusters in the data
or to find samples
closer to a specific data point
are ClusteringTree, Dendrogram,
ClusteringComponents,
FeatureSpacePlot, Nearest
and FeatureNearest.
In the absence
of labeled training samples,
ClusterClassify can be used
to build a classifier
from a clustering
of unlabeled samples,
using the clusters
as potential classes.
Finally we also looked at
LearnDistribution
and FindDistribution as ways
of learning a distribution
from the data itself to represent
the underlying process
that generated the samples.