Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 4: Assembling
a Multiparadigm Toolset.
In navigating the analyze stage
of our question-driven
multiparadigm workflow,
we've looked at questions
of the type:
Is this A or B?
How much of something
or how many items can we expect?
How is the data structured?
Are there inherent groups
to which the data samples belong?
And so on.
Next, let's take on the question
is this weird or unusual?
You know,
when faced with some data,
can we identify the samples
that seem to stand out
for whatever reason?
The unsupervised
machine learning technique
of anomaly detection
is what we would use
in such a case.
So anomaly detection would be
the tool to use
if we were attempting
to spot an attack
amidst regular network traffic
or identify
a fraudulent transaction
on a stolen credit card
amidst the usual transactions
of a regular customer
or spot
the unusual characteristics
of a diseased cell
amidst healthy tissue samples.
Outliers, or anomalies,
are data points
that are very different
from most other data points.
They are rarer.
We can find
such anomalous elements in data
using FindAnomalies.
Internally, FindAnomalies
depends on
the LearnDistribution function
we covered
in the previous segment,
which tries to learn
the underlying distribution
of the data,
given a set of examples.
LearnDistribution
and FindAnomalies
work with any type of data,
not just numbers
Given the underlying distribution
of the data,
FindAnomalies finds
the data points that are outliers
in the sense that
they should occur
only with very low probability
according to
the learned distribution.
RarerProbability computes
the probability for a distribution
to generate a sample
with a lower PDF
than the examples provided.
The AcceptanceThreshold option
can be used with FindAnomalies
to specify the value
of RarerProbability
that should be considered
very small,
and therefore cause samples
being labeled as anomalies.
Let's revisit
the Fisher's iris dataset
and try to use anomaly detection
on the samples.
The detector function can be used
to identify outliers
from a dataset,
or it can be used
to provide a verdict—
anomaly or not—
for individual samples.
RarerProbability is used to decide
which examples are outliers.
By default, any example
with a rarer probability
smaller than 0.001
is considered an outlier.
But we can change this threshold
and thus change the outlier
decision boundary for the data.
Here is another example
demonstrating how
anomaly detection can be used
on a classic dataset
containing both numerical
and nominal variables.
We have to use dimension reduction
to allow us to visualize
both the data and the anomalies
in a scatter plot.
Observe how the decision
of whether a sample
is an anomaly or not
changes with the change
in the acceptance threshold
for FindAnomalies.
Anomaly detection can easily work
on time series data as well.
For example, here is a time series
of dates and daily closing values
of the S&P 500 index
since January 1, 2015.
We can partition this data
into a list of consecutive windows
and use FindAnomalies to detect
unexpected changes
in the sequence.
Here are the detected anomalies
overlaid
on the original time series.
If we are worried
about outliers or anomalies
throwing the entire analysis
off track,
DeleteAnomalies can be used
to both find and remove
the anomalous samples
from the data in one step.
In the wrangle stage
of the workflow,
we looked at dealing
with messy data
and briefly discussed
the possibility
of using machine learning
to compute replacements
for missing data.
The unsupervised learning task
of learning a distribution
from the data
can be used to synthesize
replacements for missing values.
In this example,
we can use SynthesizeMissingValues
as a custom image in-painter.
We can first learn a distribution
for the pixel values
from the available images,
and then use it
to generate replacement values
for the missing data
in new samples.
Along with the different questions
we've looked at so far
in the analysis stage
of the question-driven
multiparadigm project workflow,
there is one we need to consider
specifically for sequential data.
Given a sequence of observations
adhering to an imposed order,
we may want to know
what comes next in the sequence.
For example, say we want to create
a text generator
that writes in the style
of a particular author—
maybe Charles Dickens.
The way to do this would be
to train a sequence predictor
on the works of Charles Dickens—
say, Tale of Two Cities.
And then once trained,
we can give a starting sequence
to the predictor
and ask it to generate text
that is most likely to come next
in the sequence.
Of course the predictions
completely depend
on the training data.
If we train our text generator
on Pride and Prejudice
instead of Tale of Two Cities,
we can expect it to generate
text sequences
in Ms. Austen's style of writing.
SequencePredict
in the Wolfram Language
internally uses the Markov model,
and we can set the order
of the Markov model
in the Method suboption.
Here the order was set
to three automatically.
Increasing it to five
does not necessarily
seem to improve
the quality of the prose.
The Wolfram Language also has
a few built-in sequence predictors
trained on text
in various languages
that can generate pseudo text
in these languages.
Here is one example
for the German sequence predictor.
Sequence prediction works
just not for text,
but also for other data.
SequencePredict allows
the modeling
of any kind of a sequence
in order to predict
its future evolution.
For example,
here is a dataset with samples
of sequences of a player's moves
in rock paper scissors.
SequencePredict can be used
to predict the next action
of the player—
whether they are going to play
rock or paper or scissors,
given his previous actions.
Now let's look at a special type
of sequential data
which have
an imposed order in time,
generally known as a time series.
We've looked a few examples
of time series data
earlier in this course.
The FinancialData function
in the Wolfram Language
returns such time series objects
which are really time-value pairs
of stock prices
or exchange rates of currencies
along with
the corresponding dates,
so the data is ordered in time.
These are the daily exchange rates
of the Euro to USD
from October 2018 to March 2019.
Since the rates are available
only for business days,
we need to resample
to ensure the time increment
is indeed a business day
and there are no gaps in the data
for the weekends.
We can fit
an auto-regressive process
on the time series data
from the past
and use it to forecast the rates
for 20 business days
in the future.
Here is a comparison
of the training data, the forecast
and the actual values for
the dates used for the forecast.
Let's look at another example
attempting to forecast
the temperature
in Champaign, Illinois,
based on the monthly temperatures
of the past 10 years.
Instead of estimating a process,
we can directly try to fit
a time series model on the data.
This is the temperature
in Champaign
as predicted by the model today.
By the way, this is really
the temperature for today.
Here are the forecasted
temperatures for 2019.
We can use the various properties
of the model
to get more information.
In summary,
we looked at two more questions
that could drive
our multiparadigm project workflow
in this segment:
1. Is this unusual?
2. What comes next?
To find out if a data point
is unusual, an anomaly
or an outlier,
we can use FindAnomalies,
which internally uses
LearnDistribution.
We looked at a few examples
of using FindAnomalies
for numeric and time series data.
We also looked at DeleteAnomalies
for finding
and deleting anomalies.
As a quick aside, we also
looked at SyntehizeMissingValues
as another use
of the LearnDistribution function
to generate replacement values
for missing data.
To answer the question
what comes next,
we looked at sequence prediction
and time series forecasting.
So in all, we have looked at
a few different questions
we can ask to get started
with a multiparadigm
data science project
and the associated
multiparadigm tools
that can help us
answer these questions.
After looking at one more tool
that has become very popular
for applying machine learning
in data science, neural networks,
we will be ready to move on
to the last stage
of our project workflow,
communicate to get
the message across,
at the end
of the project workflow.