In this course
on multiparadigm data science
with the Wolfram Language,
we looked at developing
a project workflow in stages—
question, wrangle, explore,
analyze and communicate—
and at each stage, we reviewed
the multiparadigm functionality
offered by the Wolfram Language
to implement data science tasks
required at that stage.
As we wrap up the course,
let's briefly touch
on one more topic
that is becoming
increasingly important
along with the growing
applications of data science.
It is always exciting
to report or publish
the insightful results
from a particular
data science project.
However, along with the results,
there is a growing call
for the publication
of the dataset itself
as well as the code
and other resources
used for the analysis
so that other people
can reproduce the research—
perhaps in the exact same way—
or run similar analysis
on different datasets
or try different approaches
to analyze the same data.
Publishing data-backed
reproducible analysis
makes it possible
for the broader community
to verify the results,
since replication can be construed
as stronger evidence.
Or people can build
on the existing results,
or combine results
from comparable analyses
for better insight.
The Wolfram Data Repository
is a great global resource
for publishing public data,
along with the code to analyze it.
There is more on how
the data repository can be used
for data-backed publications
in this blog post
by Stephen Wolfram.
How about a checklist
to make the research reproducible
as you plan and execute
your next data science project?
Start by building a flexible,
modular, iterative workflow
in stages.
Breaking the work down in stages
definitely helps
with the organization,
but the modularity
also makes it easier
to swap out one approach
or technique,
and swap in another one
at one particular stage
independent of the others.
Meanwhile, it is possible to go
through multiple iterations
of all the stages in the workflow,
incrementally adding to each one
as the project proceeds.
Plan for structured data analysis.
The wrangle stage of the workflow
helps in achieving this goal.
During the project execution
and most definitely
by the end of it,
the data should be
in a structured, computable form,
similar to something
that can be obtained
by traversing
the data curation hierarchy
suggested by Stephen Wolfram.
Automate the process
wherever possible.
Avoid point and click
or any sort of manual editing.
Instead, write code to implement
every task in the workflow
and to automate
the workflow itself.
No one can overemphasize the need
for documenting
and commenting all code.
This is generally true
for all software projects.
However, in data science projects
specifically,
teams comprise of people
from different backgrounds
with different expertise.
To ensure clear communication
between team members,
a documented workflow should
include, along with the code,
clear text explanations about
choice of algorithms
and parameters, as well as
visualizations or other output
generated by the code.
This is where
notebook-based workflows
become so useful.
The best practices
for data science projects
include recording
and preserving everything.
Whether it's raw data
from original sources
or initial goals of the project
and the questions
they morphed into,
references used
for making decisions
at each stage of the workflow—
all of it.
And of course,
record the process itself—
the final code used
for the analysis,
as well as all explorations,
observations and comments—
what was presented to the world
as well as what wasn't.
Version control is a no-brainer
for storing code.
Finally at the end of the project,
after sharing
the exciting results,
there's one more thing to be done
before wrapping it all up.
It's important to prepare
for obsolescence.
Life moves on;
websites get taken down;
software gets upgraded.
So hopefully
with meticulous archival,
the workflow can be reused
with the archived resources,
but it is good to have a plan B.
How would the analysis
be carried out with new data
or newer resources?
We hope you find the reproducible
research checklist useful
as you try out the multiparadigm
data science workflow
for your next project.
The Wolfram technology stack,
with more than 30 years of work
building an intuitive
easy-to-use
computation environment
with state-of-the-art algorithms,
ready-to-use data
and automation capabilities
all woven into one ecosystem,
provides all the resources
you would need
to start practicing
multiparadigm data science.