Hello and welcome
to Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 2:
Getting Your Data into Shape.
In this section,
we will look at functionality
needed for the wrangle stage
of the workflow.
Data wrangling involves
importing raw data
and converting it into
a suitable shape
for ease of use
during rest of the analysis.
A multiparadigm workflow
has to be able to handle data
in different formats
from different sources,
reshape the data
into different structures,
deal with messy data,
extract useful features from it
and, if needed,
reduce dimensionality
of high-dimensional data.
While dealing with all of this,
the goal is to write code
for a set of automated tools
for the data-wrangling process
so that it is much easier
to go through this stage
next time the workflow is used.
Let's look at some examples
of importing real-world data
from different sources.
In best-case scenarios,
high-quality curated data may
be available from repositories.
For data that has been
curated properly,
there really is no need
for much wrangling—
for example,
the Wolfram Data Repository,
which is a publicly
available resource
for computable datasets.
It has curated
and structured data
available for immediate use.
We can browse the site
for datasets by category
or by type.
The data is all cleaned
and ready for computation.
So if we find a dataset
that we'd like to use,
we can just load it
into our system
and start working with it.
In addition to the
data repository,
the Wolfram Language has an
extensive built-in knowledgebase
that can be explored
for interesting data,
or it can also be leveraged
to augment
some existing in-house data
with additional information.
To access this knowledgebase,
we can simply
type in words in English,
which are then interpreted
into canonical entities
representing real-world objects.
We can access the various
properties of these entities
and use them for computation.
There are millions of entities
across hundreds of entity types
built into the Wolfram Language.
Also, there are collections
of domain-specific datasets
like geographic data,
engineering and medical data,
social, cultural
and linguistic data.
So that's curated data,
but most people want to import
their own data into the system.
And we can do that
with a simple import statement
for files residing either locally
on the computer
or online on the web.
To support
a multiparadigm workflow,
the Wolfram Language can handle
a wide variety of formats.
The Import function
automatically deals
with the format of the file
when importing data from it.
Sometimes it is useful to save
data and intermediate results
in the middle of the workflow.
Data can be saved
as Wolfram Language expressions
using Save or DumpSave,
and then read back in again
using Get.
Okay, now let's
move on to databases.
In many projects,
data is available
in a relational database,
so the multiparadigm workflow
must be able to connect
to the database
and get the data from it.
Here's an example of opening
a connection to a database,
looking at the tables in it
and fetching data from a table
using a Wolfram Language
function.
Alternately we can use
standard SQL to fetch the data
and work with it.
It is also possible to represent
a relational database
symbolically
in the Wolfram Language
by constructing an EntityStore.
This allows the relational data
from the database
to be structured as entities,
very much like
the built-in entities
in the Wolfram Data Framework.
So now we can we can use
the same syntax to query
and use the properties of
these entities for computation.
Moving on to the world wide web,
which is another
major source of data,
there are multiple different ways
of getting data from the web.
Many online services
provide APIs,
which can be used to import
the data from these services.
Here is an example of connecting
to the Twitter API
and downloading tweets made by
a specific Twitter handle.
Or we can simply search the web
for generic content
or maybe specify the type of
content we'd like to search for.
Wikipedia is another
great resource,
and it can be searched
not only for text,
but other metadata as well.
Finally, if we are just given
a URL,
we can simply scrape
the data off the webpage.
Depending on the requirements
of the project,
we may have to scrape everything
available on the webpage
and then parse the raw data
to make sense of it,
or we can scrape specific
elements like images
or hyperlinks from the page.
So that covers a number
of different data sources
that we can work with when
we are trying to wrangle data.
Some of us may already have
some in-house data
that we would like to analyze
as we follow the project workflow
in this course.
But for those who are looking
for interesting datasets
to work with, here are some
publicly available resources
to get started.
We've already looked
at the Wolfram Data Repository.
The US Government's
open data website
is another great resource;
so is NASA's Open Data Portal,
UCI's Machine
Learning Repository,
the Kaggle contests,
the Five Thirty Eight
blog collections
and so on.
In summary, in this segment,
we looked at importing data
from different sources—
loading it into the system
for exploration and analysis.
We looked at getting curated data
from the Wolfram Data Repository
and built-in
Wolfram Knowledgebase,
and we also looked
at simply importing data
from files
in a variety of formats,
residing either locally
or online on the web.
We looked at connecting to APIs
to download data
from online services,
and last but not the least,
we looked at scraping
data elements off webpages.
We hope you will be able to use
one or more of these options
in the wrangling stage
of your project.
In the next segment, we will
look at restructuring data
to make it ready for use
in various stages
further downstream
in the workflow.