Multiparadigm Data Science
with the Wolfram Language,
Section 1: The Project Workflow.
We are now at the third stage
of the project workflow,
that is, explore.
We will try some exploratory
data analysis
for our example project,
where we downloaded the tweets
made by Wolfram Research
and are hoping to use them to
derive some data-driven insights.
Exploratory data analysis
is all about trying to gain
an intuitive understanding
of the data.
We don't have to know exactly
what sort of algorithm
or technique we want to employ
for the data yet.
In fact,
with the multiparadigm workflow,
we are encouraged
to keep an open mind
and try out different techniques.
There is no wrong choice
at this point,
and this makes it much more fun.
As the exploration proceeds,
we may even find ourselves
reframing the questions
we started out with.
Let's explore the Twitter data
and figure out if it can be used
to answer questions like:
How many tweets were made?
What were the tweets
talking about?
Who was featured in these tweets?
And so on.
To answer the question,
"how many tweets were sent out,"
we can look at the DateHistogram
showing the number of tweets
by year.
We can recreate
the same date histogram,
but this time binning the tweets
by the day of the week
on which they were created.
This shows that
the majority of the tweets
went out on Wednesday.
In another version
of the histogram,
we can bin the tweets
by hour of the day.
We see most of the tweets
were made
during regular business hours,
but someone was burning the
midnight oil at these tail ends.
While we are exploring
the numbers,
it would be nice to know
how many tweets
were liked or retweeted
a certain number of times.
So here is a histogram
of the number of times
a tweet was liked.
We see that the majority
of the tweets were liked
anywhere between 0 and 25 times,
while when we look
at the retweets,
in the same way,
we see very few tweets
were retweeted
more than 400 times.
We can actually pull out
these tail-end tweets
liked or retweeted more than
a certain number of times
and look at their text
and hashtags.
Now that we have explored
the numbers a bit,
let's explore the actual content
of these tweets.
We can look at the hashtags
in the tweets
to see what Wolfram Research
has been tweeting about.
A plain list is not very useful,
so maybe we could count and sort
the hashtags in descending order
of number of times they were used.
But the same information
becomes more appealing visually
in a word cloud,
and seems like this would be
a good way to convey
the importance given
to certain hashtags
or specific topics in the tweets.
Here is a word cloud made out
of the raw text from the tweets,
and it is immediately visible
that the text text
needs some cleaning.
There—much better once we use
the cleanText function
we developed before.
In addition to the hashtags
and user mentions,
a few other
interesting words pop up.
It appears that we announce
a lot of new things
and we are also very polite,
as we say a lot of thanks,
and we also encourage
people to learn.
Next let's explore to see
who were the people in the tweets.
We did look at the users
mentioned in the tweets.
We can create a word cloud
with that information
and can see who
was mentioned most often.
Well, no surprise there.
We have the Twitter handles
of these users,
but we could get more information
if we could download
the user data.
So back to
the data wrangling stage
to download and organize
some more data for these users.
You'll notice a few errors
while we try to download the data
because not all accounts
make the information
publicly downloadable.
But for the ones that are
successfully downloaded,
let's see what is available.
We have the user ID; screen name,
or the Twitter handle;
display name; location;
favorites count;
and friends count.
Notice there is no consistency
in the way the location
information is provided.
Sometimes we have
the city and state
or just the city
or just the country
or nothing at all.
Now a little data cleaning
can get us
from these place names
in natural language
to actual geographic coordinates,
and for that we can use
the ComputedLocation interpreter
in the Wolfram Language.
It easily converts the text
in natural language
to usable geographic coordinates
that can be plotted on a map.
In fact with a GeoHistogram,
we can see the density
of the users on a world map,
which provides some indication
of the regions
where most of these users
who were mentioned
in the Wolfram tweets
are located.
We had seen in
the earlier word clouds
what the Wolfram Research tweets
were talking about.
It would be interesting to see
what the tweets by all these users
who are being mentioned
by Wolfram Research—
what are they talking about?
So back to data wrangling again
to download the hashtags
used by these users.
And laying them out
in a word cloud,
we see shared interest in AI,
machine learning,
data science, blockchain
and of course Wolfram Language
and Mathematica.
In case you are wondering,
Chambana, here,
is how folks refer
to the twin cities
of Champaign–Urbana,
Champaign being the location of
Wolfram's corporate headquarters.
Branching out into
a different path of exploration,
we can try to look at
the social network of these users:
who is being mentioned by whom
and how they are connected
through such user mentions.
First let's download the people
who are mentioned
in the tweets made by all these
other people in our list.
Some people do not mention others,
so their list is empty.
If we draw an edge
from one user to another
every time the former
mentions the latter,
we can create the network
of users mentioning each other.
So let's shortlist
the people for whom
the right-hand side
is not an empty list,
that is, people who mention
at least one other person
in their tweets,
and create a list
of edges going out
from each node
in our prospective graph.
A whole bunch of edges
will connect Wolfram Research
to people in our list.
This is the graph showing
all the connections.
It has over 13,000 vertices
and 16,000 edges.
So let's try to focus
on a simpler subgraph.
For every user mention,
the node representing that user
has an edge coming into the node.
These edges make up
the in-degree of the node.
The most popular person
in the network—
most mentioned by others—
would have the highest in-degree.
We pick the vertices
with in-degree above a threshold,
choosing people mentioned
at least a certain number
of times in this network,
and attempt to visualize
this simpler subgraph.
This picture is much clearer,
but we could probably
scale the vertex size
according to the in-degrees
so that we can at once see
which are the more popular nodes.
Exploratory analysis can be
the most fun part
of your project,
so sometimes you just
have to put the brakes
on exploration before
you get carried off
with the fun and ease
of doing such analysis.
We have tried a bunch of things,
and now have some ideas
about the type of insights we
might be able draw from the data.
We also came up
with some new questions
that can be asked, and also
additional data that can be used
to augment the data
we started out with.
Armed with these thoughts,
we can move on to the analysis
phase of the workflow.