Welcome to Section 1
of Introduction to Image Processing.
This section provides an overview
of typical image processing tasks
and some examples of topics
that are covered in this course.
The first step in almost
any image processing task
is getting the images
into the computer
or importing the images
into the software that will be
used for the processing.
One way of doing that
is by connecting the computer
and the software to a camera.
This shows
the CurrentImage function
in the Wolfram Language,
which captures an image
from a camera
connected to this computer
and imports the image
into this Wolfram Language system.
You can also import images
from files on your computer
or from the internet.
For example, this imports
a JPEG image
from a file on the internet.
JPEG is one of dozens
of common image formats.
Images can also be generated
within the computer.
For example,
this uses the Image function
to create an image
from a table of numbers.
Images can also be created
from things displayed
on the computer screen.
For example, this displays a plot
and then uses
the Rasterize function
to convert that display
to an image.
The image can then be edited
or modified like any other image.
After an image has been imported,
there is a variety of things
that can be done
to modify the image,
either for aesthetic reasons
or to prepare the image
for further analysis.
For example,
this shows a Manipulate result
with controls for modifying
the brightness and contrast
in an image.
Operations for adjusting
brightness and contrast
are discussed in Sections 2 and 3.
Contrast and brightness adjustment
work by changing
the image histogram,
which is the distribution
of colors
and intensities in an image.
There are
several common operations
that involve other modifications
of the image histogram.
For example,
this shows an operation
called color transfer
or histogram matching,
which modifies the distribution
of colors in one image
to match the distribution
of colors in another image.
Histogram matching
and some related operations
are discussed in Section 4.
Another group
of basic image operations
is geometric operations
like cropping and rotating
and resizing the image.
For example, this shows
a cropped and rotated version
of the sample image
created using the ImageRotate
and ImageTrim functions.
Here is a Manipulate result
that shows
these geometric operations
with sliders to control
the amount of cropping
and resizing and rotating.
Basic geometric operations
are covered in Section 8.
A key step
in many image processing tasks
is segmentation,
which means separating out
different parts of the image.
There are many methods
of segmentation.
This shows segmentation
using the Binarize function,
which separates the image
into two segments
based on brightness.
The result from segmentation
is represented here
by a black-and-white image,
with the bright segment identified
by the white parts of that result
and the darker segment
identified by the black parts.
Once the image
has been segmented,
there are many things
that can be done with it.
For example, this picks out
the biggest connected components
in that segmentation,
which in this example
are the slices of the pizza.
This input uses the
ComponentMeasurements function
to count the number of pieces
of pizza in that segmentation
and give the size of each piece.
The general topic of segmentation
and specifically segmentation
using the Binarize function
are covered in Section 5.
It is also worth noting
that those last two inputs
illustrate an area
of image processing
called image analysis,
where the goal is to get
information from the image
instead of just modifying
the image to get another image.
There are many other methods
of segmentation.
One method is clustering,
which can, for example,
segment an image by grouping
similar colors in an image.
This shows segmentation
by clustering
used to separate the sample image
into five segments.
The Colorize function is used here
to display each segment
in a contrasting color.
Another method of segmentation
is watershed segmentation.
As an example, this input
shows a watershed algorithm
used to separate a satellite image
into components
on opposite sides of a river.
Segmentation by clustering
is described in Section 7,
and other methods of segmentation
are described in Section 11.
One use of an image segment
is as a mask
to provide a way to do things
to selected parts of an image.
For example,
this shows a segmentation
that separates the pizza
from everything else in the image,
and this uses that segment
as a mask
to remove color from everything
other than the masked part
of the image.
So the background
becomes black and white
and the pizza remains in color.
There are many other things
that can be done with color.
Here is an input that uses
the ColorDistance function
to segment the image based
on similarity to the color green,
which identifies the green things
on the pizza.
These operations
and some basic color theory
are discussed in Section 6.
Another broad area
of image processing
is image enhancement,
which includes tools
for reducing noise in images
and for repairing defects
in images.
For example, here is a noisy
version of the sample image,
And this input shows
smoothing out the noise
using a Gaussian filter.
There are many other methods
of noise reduction.
This shows a method
called a mean shift filter
that does a slightly better job
of removing the noise
while preserving sharp edges
in the image.
Image defects
can often be corrected
using a method called inpainting,
which works by filling in defects
using colors and textures
from the surrounding parts
of the image.
For inpainting,
the part of the image
that is to be filled in
is identified by a mask.
This shows inpainting
used with a mask
that identifies everything
other than the pizza
as the part of the image
that is to be filled in,
which basically
removes the background.
With a few adjustments,
the background can also
be filled in with more pizza.
Tools for noise reduction
and other image enhancements
are discussed in Section 9.
Section 10 covers the general
topic of feature detection.
In many applications,
it is important to identify
basic features of an image
like lines and edges.
For example,
this shows the ImageLines function
used to detect lines in an image.
In this example,
those lines could be useful
for subsequent operations
such as removing
perspective distortion.
Depending on the application,
almost anything on an image
could be a feature.
For example, this uses
the ImageKeypoints function
to identify a certain class
of potentially
interesting features in an image.
Those features could be important
in a variety of applications,
such as, for example,
trimming the image based on
the locations of features.
Section 12 describes
a diverse class of operations
that use ideas
from mathematical morphology,
which typically means
that these operations work
by considering relationships
between neighboring locations
in an image.
For example, this shows
a morphological operation
called a top-hat transform,
used to remove the large features
and the variation
in background shading
from an image.
The result is an image
that emphasizes
the finer details
of the original image.
This shows
another morphological operation
called geodesic dilation,
which is used here to reconstruct
two paths through a circuit
based on a marker image
that identifies starting points
on those two paths.
A particularly active area
of new development
in image processing is
application of machine learning,
which is covered in Section 13.
For example,
this shows the FindFaces function,
which uses
a machine learning algorithm
to find human faces in an image.
Here is another example.
This shows
the ImageIdentify function,
which uses
a machine learning algorithm
that has been trained to identify
the main object in an image.
In addition to
these built-in functions,
there is a large and growing
collection of functions
in the Wolfram Neural
Net Repository.
Neural nets are a common method
used in machine learning.
Section 13 includes
several examples
from the Neural Net Repository.
The final section, Section 14,
is a set of examples
chosen to illustrate
how the techniques covered
in earlier sections
can be used
in complete applications.
This shows stabilization
of a shaky video,
which is one of the examples
in Section 14.
That’s the end of the examples
for this section.
Here is the outline for this course,
which is designed to use
practical examples
to provide a foundation
for solving problems
in image processing.